<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tree of faith: or, The tree of life, springing up in the paradise of God; : from which all the wonders of the new Creation, in the virgin church of the first-born of wisdom must proceed. / By J. Lead.</title>
            <author>Lead, Jane, 1623-1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L791</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R179388</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077524</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077524</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151593</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88858)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151593)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2266:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tree of faith: or, The tree of life, springing up in the paradise of God; : from which all the wonders of the new Creation, in the virgin church of the first-born of wisdom must proceed. / By J. Lead.</title>
                  <author>Lead, Jane, 1623-1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 222 [i.e 122], [12], 23 [i.e 32], [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by J. Bradford, in Fewen-Street, near Crowder's-Well,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The ark of faith: or A supplement to The tree of faith, &amp;c." ([12], 23 [i.e. 32] p. at end) has special title page and separate paging.</note>
                  <note>P. [122] misprinted as 222; p. [32] at end misprinted as 23.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: [2] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles, California.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mysticism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Paradise --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:151593:1"/>
                  <p>THE TREE of FAITH: OR, <hi>The Tree of Life,</hi> Springing up in the <hi>Paradiſe of GOD;</hi> From which All the Wonders of the New Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, in the Virgin Church of the Firſt-born of Wiſdom muſt proceed.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>J. Lead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Matth. 13.32.</hi>
                     </bibl> It is the Leaſt of all Seeds: but when it is grown, it is the Greateſt of Herbs, and becometh a TREE.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>J. Bradford,</hi> in <hi>Jewen-Street,</hi> near <hi>Crowder's</hi>-Well, 1696.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:151593:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:151593:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>HAving given an Account of the Confuſion of the <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh</hi> Forms, being rejected by the Head Shepherd; from whom an Angel is gone forth that hath ſounded the Trumpet, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim, That all Formal Worſhips ſet up by Man, and conſtituted by Rational Inventions, as a Shadow muſt paſs away: For no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this Day ſhall ſtand but the Power and Spirit of the Lamb; that will caſt up his Church into no other Mold, but that in which he himſelf in his Reſurrection-State did Appear
<pb facs="tcp:151593:3"/>So that the Gathering together of his Flocks from all Parts, ſhall be for the making up this Reſurrection Church, as New born into the <hi>Faith.</hi> For which Reaſon I have here ſuperadded a Manifeſtation, which ſome Years ſince was given me; which I judge may now be of as General <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe to make Publick, as it was firſt for my own Particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and Inſtruction: whence it was never deſign'd to ſee the Light. But ſeeing that this Church that hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd by the Spirit of Chriſt, is to conſiſt of the Branches of Faith, growing up from the Root and Stock of <hi>Abraham;</hi> it was found very Expedient that this ſhould follow the foregoing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe: Becauſe the New Creation which is to be brought forth, muſt have their Conſiſtency of
<pb facs="tcp:151593:3"/>Life, by the Faith of the Son of God; that as he was in this World, ſo may alſo his Bride and Spouſe be, acting in the Holy Ghoſtly Property, to do the Wonders which the Laſt Age of the World is to produce. For it is expected that mighty Deeds and Works ſhall be wrought by this New Riſen Virgin Church, ſuch as have, and ſuch as never have been: For the Patriarchs, Prophets, and moſt highly Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Faith and Love, Power and Purity, ſhall again deſcend, to aſſume Perſons that are of this Reſurrection Life, ſo to do all the Worthy Exploits, according to the Lot in which each Antient Saint did ſtand. All which ſhall be renewed again, for the ſtate of the Propheſies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to Chriſt's thouſand Years Reign: which will overſpread
<pb facs="tcp:151593:4"/>the Earth with the Kingly, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical, and Prieſtly Train.</p>
                  <p>I had ſome thoughts of Oblite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating the beginning of this little Treatiſe, being only a Private Recollection of my Spiritual Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, which I have uſed to make from Year to Year; but I quickly check'd my ſelf herein, for that it was mov'd upon me, that it might be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful and Beneficial to ſome Souls, and for a Pattern to excite them to the Recollection; Wherefore I reſolved to let it go, without any Alteration., accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to its full and Genuine Senſe.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>J. L.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151593:4"/>
                  <head>THE <hi>Tree of Faith,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p n="1">§. 1. BEing come to the Concluſion of this Year 1686. recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting and making Obſervation from one New-Year to another of what hath paſſed both in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Internal Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Growths and Degrees arrived to in Spirituals, and what hath happened by ſpecial Providence concerning the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Bodily Man, both which I have for ſome Years kept a Memorandum of, for my own private ſatisfaction, taking ſpecial notice how the Work of God hath gone on in order to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151593:5"/>perfecting of what my Soul hath been theſe many Years in great travail for, but in ſpecial for what hath been in ſight and view through the Spirit of Prophecy, declared unto me ſince 1670. in the which Year, and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on to this time, entring upon this New Year, I have found the working Wheel from the ſtrong Hand of the Moſt High, and have driven hard on for the bringing back of my Soul into Eternal and pure Nature's Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginalty again: the which to be plain, is no leſs then to be Born again into another World, where this viſible Birth in Sin, with its world, is as forgotten, and ſhut out: no otherwiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, but to give occaſion of the greateſt Wonder, and admiration of that great and infinite goodneſs that hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fettered,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151593:5"/>and ſet the Soul free, to be born into a divine and ſpiritual Body, ſo to dwell and inhabit in the high and heavenly World, where my Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency hath been maintained much ſince the Year 70. gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Year by Year ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and higher degree of Wiſdom and Underſtanding in the ſecret Myſteries of Eternity, as to what doth lie hidden there: which through our ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction of Mind, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Attendance, in new Varieties from that World do preſent themſelves.</p>
                  <p n="2">§. 2. Now as to this laſt paſt Year, many have been my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal provings, and ſecret Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates that have followed me hard, to ſhake my Faith as to the great and wonderful Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151593:6"/>relating to the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of a full and perfect Redeemed State among Mortals, here to be ſeen and known, in order to which I have been fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with renewed Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Promiſes for the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up and open the Springs of Faith, which otherwiſe would have been ſtopped; therefore I muſt proclaim the goodneſs of God, who hath kept the ſtock of Faith going on in me, for the hopeful conſummating of what is yet behind, which are great and weighty things, worth waiting upon; which if ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully I may attain, will quit all ſuffering loſs of what ever can be called Earthly and Terrene in ſenſible things, which are of this World, only among Mortals ſeen, from all which I have been much called from: as finding
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151593:6"/>every Year hath renewed upon me great abatements, and weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Life and Love to all periſhable things. A good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon there is why; becauſe the Heavens do before me open ſtand, by which my Mind and Spirit is ſo well entertained, by the Objects there ſeen with all ſubſtantial Varieties, that I need not care any more to look out for theſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">§. 3. When at any time drawn and pluck'd away I am by ſtrong motives from this World, then great Wo, Pain and Trouble do me poſſeſs; for ſo it is when at any time I am out of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Places, where now only my Life doth lie, within that ſecret Cabinet of Eternity, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring that as my chief and only Excellency. So I reſolve to go
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151593:7"/>forward by the Power of the Moſt High this enſuing Year, for what of this kind may mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply and proſper in my Hand mightily. For the which all care and ſtrict Watch I ſee muſt be, that ſo I may not overſlip my Day, acting accordingly as Power doth move and riſe, the which is to be attended upon Day by Day, as God ſhall clear up the way, otherwiſe all At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts are but in vain, which ſet upon may be, as I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by what hath been under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken contrary to this all high and approving Eye. Therefore Wiſdom doth me teach in a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive brokenneſs of Will to ſtand, till my God ſhall come forth with the Expreſs Word of Command; that ſo the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Plantation may go on, and nothing it withſtand: for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151593:7"/>lets and interpoſings have got in: as I have from Year to Year ſeen, and will be ſtill, I do find, until the Spirit of Faith do get the upper-hand, which in God the driver on is to be, that ſo the long ſet back Work in Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſt Day, may after ſo many Years delay come forward once again. For the which I have been a private and earneſt wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and diligent ſeeker, where ever I might find Spirits that hereunto were inclined, to wait in a pure Temple-mind united<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the great Dowry of the Holy Power again to riſe: but to this Day a ſcattering and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding among the Holy People hath been; who hitherto are ſcared and affrighted away from each other, upon poor, low and worldly Circumſtances; ſo as no Body of Saints can yet get
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151593:8"/>together. The which hath been very grievous unto me, carrying a ſecret Sorrow and Mourning in my Soul here for: I having ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the power given me, made offers here and there; but oh how little hath this Call been underſtood? No not even by thoſe who might become of the high and holy waiting Diſciplehood; ſo as that upon this account, in long-ſuffering I have been look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this way, and that way, for the moſt holy Wind to blow ſome one or other in for a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, into this great and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Gathering.</p>
                  <p n="4">§. 4. I have often ſeen my own Angel Spirit fluttering to and fro, from Plant to Plant, and ſo on to each <hi>Lebanon</hi>-Tree, to find where the Eagle-Body might make her Neſt, her
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151593:8"/>Young there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Hatch and Brood in ſafety from the ravenous Birds of Prey: but no ſooner was I here alighted, after many a long Flight, but the flying Serpent hath with great ſury come forth, to prevent, and demoliſh what was prepared for this intent, and ſo hath often permitted been hitherto to keep off a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected gathering, as a Heaven-Born Society, which by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together, may make up the holy Prieſtly Body, whom God may give witneſs unto, by pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them his Tabernacle-Preſence, in great Power and Glory. O for this, how hath my Soul and Spirit been carried forth to ſeek and wait upon it? and ſtill muſt it purſue, till my God ſhall it fulfil, as decreed it is in his Will.</p>
                  <p n="5">§. 5. Now as to what hath
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151593:9"/>paſſed this preſent Year relating to the outward Being, with all Circumſtances thereunto rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, it hath been very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and worth taking notice of. Wherein my God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared greatly for my ſupport, anſwering all Bodily Neceſſities, which hath been brought in by a ſignal Hand of renewed Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as occaſion hath requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Although great plunges and difficulties, with Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereupon attending, for my proving, did meet upon me, for the tryal of my Faith. Which the Power of the Moſt High did ſtill maintain and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold inviſibly, and thereby brought me forth out of all moſt victoriouſly. My Tribulations and Diſtreſſes were known to God only: For I ſaw it in vain to complain to any Creaturely Being: but ſtill in all I did
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151593:9"/>apply my ſelf to that Name Great <hi>JEHOVAH:</hi> whom I found a Refuge at all times very nigh, procuring delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance oft-times unexpectedly. For the which great goodneſs from my God thus by me proved, I have ſo much to ſay and make mention of by way of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and praiſe, that the number of Times and Days are far too little, to rehearſe and proclaim the Bounteouſneſs of this great Love, that hath thus minded me in a deſolate Widow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ſtate. But what I may be ſhort of in Time, let Eternity while in Time, and out, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all time, for ever celebrate one Everlaſting Sabbath of Laud, with pure and powerful Praiſes to thee oh, Holy, Holy, Holy, Infinite Almighty! whom my Soul doth ſo greatly adore, that Silence muſt ſpeak much
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151593:10"/>more, with a Life that muſt excel both.</p>
                  <p n="6">§. 6. Now waiting ſtill upon thee, O God, for what may further produce this Approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Year, in order to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of what hath been the main drift, and whole Scope of my Life's attendency, ſince the unſealing of the Heavenly Myſtery. By which the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation hath preſſed in ſo deep upon me, that hath made me to relinquiſh all impeding Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicities which poſſiby I could wind my ſelf off from, that ſo I might follow on in pure Heart Spiritual-mindedneſs, that ſo I might be a partaker and a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor of what is to follow, as hath been accordingly made known through the Spirit of Revelation unto me, which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151593:10"/>have raiſed all the powers and forces of my Soul for the giving up it ſelf to this high and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Calling, which is the Holy Profeſſion of Faith, which now my Life that I am henceforth to live muſt wholly conſiſt of; for ſo my Lord hath averred and eſtabliſhed his Word renewedly unto me.</p>
                  <p n="7">§. 7. The Spirit doth hard upon me for this ply, declaring unto me, that upon Faith's bottom I muſt ſtand and go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on all ſteadily: the Work is great which I do ſtand charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able withal, for the which, oh God, my own ſtrength is but ſmall, therefore to thy Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency I do call, for that muſt be my all in all, to make me a Practitioner in this high and Heavenly Calling. The Matter
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151593:11"/>which I have to work upon, is only from that Word of Faith, which did create all Worlds: the which doth greatly ſupport and ſatisfie, and ſupport me as a ſtock of ſtrength and power, that will carry on to Victory, keeping my Eye always ſtaid hereupon; as the Prieſtly Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is ſet out for me, who no Propriety have among the Tribes, whoſe Inheritances are of another kind: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord will ſtill my Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be in full, for all things that ſhall needful be.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Viſion of the Tree.</head>
                     <p n="8">§. 8. Now in order to this, there was ſhewn to me a Tree that ſhould all ſuddenly ſpring up in me, which ſpread forth its Branches for increaſe and fruitfulneſs: and that no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151593:11"/>would have upon any other Tree but it ſelf. Which was intituled to me to be <hi>Faith's Tree,</hi> on which, without fear, the Eagle-Bird may build her Neſt, and not be diſturbed, while ſhe is hatching her moſt holy Prieſtly Brood, who from the Fruits of this Tree are to be fed, and nouriſhed, till unto ſuch ſtrength arrived, as to take their flight tranſcendently, up unto their own Prieſtly Thrones, near to CHRIST their Prieſtly Head, there to meet that Company, which of their own Royal ſort and kind, in ſacred and pure White Robes all cloathed are. So that here a mutual fellowſhip betwixt the lower and higher Worlds, all agreeably will be, which is the great Wonder that in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens hath lately been opened
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151593:12"/>to me, not for Speculation only, but for Provocation, to ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Work, with ſuch as ſhall hereunto added unto me be. For the which a pure bright attractive Eye is gone forth, to fetch in ſuch as are numbred to ſtand with me, while the Eagle-Spirit is hatching her Young upon Faith's Tree.</p>
                     <p n="9">§. 9. Which Tree, I find, can grow upon no other Soil, but a Ground all purely refined with oily Springs and Dews from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which muſt its watering be. Then will it ſpread and flouriſh all richly, having fruitfulneſs in it ſelf, without any depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency. Oh! this is the Tree that will us bleſs, with Wiſdom, Strength and Righteouſneſs: for the which I find it in my Heart moſt earneſtly to ſeek and pray,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151593:12"/>that it may be moſt choicely kept, and circled round about, with the pure Love Fire, blown up by the Holy Ghoſt. Which may its ſhelter be from all the invading Spirits, that ſo dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently do watch to break in, to crop and ſuck away its ſtrength. For this, O my God, an holy awful fear is upon me, becauſe I do well know what damage and ſpoil it hath occured, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it of low and little ſtature, to prevent what might be the World's Conqueſt, and great working Wonder. Therefore now, my God, what is to be done for its preſervation? Make me privy in the Secrecy of act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo wiſe a part, as few, or none have in this later Age found out, and why is it ſo, but becauſe no skilful Artiſt in this Myſtery of Faith, hath been
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151593:13"/>made to underſtand the way, for the preſerving and cheriſhing this choice Golden Grain, from whence this Tree of Faith might to its full growth attain.</p>
                     <p n="10">§. 10. For the which ſuch Rules preſcribed are, and reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto me by the only wiſe Counſellor, my Friend: which if I can obſerve and obey, I may then win the Day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> God's great working Powers thereby for to diſplay, much more then have been in former Days. But the way is ſuch an averſion to what in the whole Univerſe of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind is practiſed, that it will be a difficult point to enter here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, ſo as to hold on; for here is required a croſſing of the Tide and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m of Nature in all its motions which do put forth, and generate ſo aptly. Againſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151593:13"/>which reſiſt in the Faith I muſt all ſtedfaſtly till Conqueſt be wrought out by the growth of this all-powerful Tree.</p>
                     <p n="11">§. 11. This hath been ſhewn me to branch forth it ſelf in twelve riſing Degrees, for the Manifeſtation of the Antient Apoſtolical Faith: which in this Age is to be recovered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, for the cutting ſhort that Work which in thouſands of Years many Holy Souls have been puzling and ſtriving about, while ſticking in the wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and low degrees of Faith. From the conſideration of which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe a mighty ſtirring up I feel, ſo to preſs on, as to reach to all of theſe twelve degrees, which from that ſmall Muſtard-Grain Seed of Faith ſown by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in me, may to ſuch a great
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151593:14"/>and full increaſe ſpread out it ſelf, as may tranſcend the growth of all other Trees that in the Foreſt of this World do ſtand bound down with Iron Yokes, and Bands; now the twelve De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of this Tree in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Properties were thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed unto me.</p>
                     <p n="1">§. 12. 1. The firſt degree of this Faith, is to believe the apoſtacy and ruinous heap and matter of which the Body of Sin is contracted into.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. A ſecond degree, is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that this Degeneracy hath parted the Soul from God, and made it a Stranger to all Knowledge, and Poſſeſſion of thoſe high and precious and choice things, which might have been the propriety of the Soul in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151593:14"/>God, had it not gone out from him.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The third degree is to believe there is left a Spark or Seed of Eternity in all Mankind, which may incline and turn them in, ſo to feel after God, as to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment bitterly their own Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. A fourth degree is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Eternal Word was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnated in Fleſh for a Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Redemption, and Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration out of this lapſed ſtate, through Faith in him, for the begetting a Likeneſs and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity through an Eſſential Birth, brought forth in Spirit, all evidently.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. A fifth degree is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there is an All-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency in CHRIST thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and brought forth in Spirit internally, within the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151593:15"/>Soul's eſſential part as may have power to purge, refine, ſave, and cleanſe the Soul from all its Sins.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. The ſixth degree is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and expect the Holy Ghoſt to come to join, and co-operate with this new begetting Birth, for the bringing it up, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing it from all Aſſaults, Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>, and Temptations; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ing an holy Clarification, che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ing and ſtrengthning it, till it be ſtrong to go forth for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtration, to ſhew it ſelf to the World as thus regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. A ſeventh degree, is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and witneſs that Chriſt his riſen Life in the Soul, doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a death to the Body of Sin totally, which we may call a <hi>Love Kiſs,</hi> whereby Chriſt doth ſweetly, and ſeceretly draw,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151593:15"/>and part the Soul from all the dregs and relicks that appertain to a Lapſed Nature, which is known by a power working ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturally.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. An eighth degree is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that when all this is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, Chriſt will appear in the Soul without Sin, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it unto the Father, as a new created Wonder, all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated to be his Spouſe and Bride, rejoycing that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Lamb is come, all things therefore being made ready.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. A ninth degree, is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that Chriſt the Lord will not fail to perform the ſacred Nuptial and Marriage-Union, both for Time and Eternity, with the Spirit of the Bride thus made ready, and will own and confeſs her ſo to be his choice,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151593:16"/>before his Father and the whole Aſſembly of Angels and Elders, Principalities and Powers in Heavenly Places: and alſo here upon the Earth ſhall ſo owned be for her Excellency, as ſhall be an all-amazing Glory.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. A tenth degree, is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that hereupon will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low all mutual Joys and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, in Love Feſtival Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetting which ſhe is ſo taken up and raviſhed in, as all former Mournings and Sorrows are forgotten, coming no more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Mind: ſo ineffable are the Bride's So lacements with the Lord her Bridegroom.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. The eleventh is to believe that Chriſt will ſettle upon this eſpouſed Bride all that is his: that ſhe ſhall have a mutual In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt with him, in what the Father hath put into his Hand,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151593:16"/>which is all Power, and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to manage that power; which reacheth to a dominion in, and over all created Beings, and Things, whatever: herein for certainty ſhe will be put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Joint-poſſeſſion, with the Lord her Bridegroom, as her Propriety.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. Twelfthly and Laſtly, as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>m of all, is to believe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtly, that after this Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentive Bride of the Lamb, ſo declared in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> World to be by her Ornamental Gifts, and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Powers, that will gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly go forth for the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying and making up of the pure ſpotleſs Virgin Church here on Earth, will the Lord from Heaven deſcend in great and high ſtate to fetch his Bride the Church, up to his Fathers Houſe, or Royal City, for the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151593:17"/>conſummating and celebrating ſuch a Tryumphant Glory, in U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with the Body of Saints, that are in Heavenly Places before hand, even ſuch a Glory through the Spirit, until we come there into the very ſame Glory, as Chriſt had with the Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Worlds were, which is too great to be known here.</p>
                     <p n="13">§. 13. Thus having had all the Degrees and Branches of Faith's Tree opened, and ſet before me, for Tryal, Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and Information: not only in particular for my ſelf, but for ſuch as do agree to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend with me, and go forward on to all theſe Degrees; for the which God hath choſen ſome one or other, that are made all willing to give up hereunto, by waiting upon it until the great
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151593:17"/>Operator ſhall bring forth this Tree in its full ſtature; that the Eagle-Spirits may find all variety of Food for themſelves, and therewith greatly increaſe in all kind of Subſtance, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being beholding to the World; for it hath been teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied unto me, and that from a ſure Hand, that the Eagle and her Brood ſhall in all Worlds have command, for the which I received an expreſs charge to wait all believingly with ſuch as hereunto are with me to agree, for the full accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe Gifts and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous working Powers, which ſo long have been ſilenced and laid aſleep: and by whom are theſe to be awakned, but by the cloſe ſetters, and conſtant feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers upon Faith's Tree who are not to hitch off and on; for if
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151593:18"/>ſo, the Work of Faith will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver go on.</p>
                     <p n="14">§. 14. The Spirit of my God hath opened this Senſe deep up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me for the bewailing of Faith's apoſtacy, and how that the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> waiters in this Spirit have been along time ſcattered, and carried captive into <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the moſt holy Veſſels and Things prophaned, (ſo conſidered in a Spiritual Senſe) and the anointed Holy Place, where the great High Prieſt's entrance ſhould be, is greatly demoliſhed, and made common for unclean and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirits to paſs in, and ſo hath brought in great confuſion. Now it is much ſet upon me to ſtrengthen the feeble Hands of Faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the recovery of this All commanding and Powerful
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151593:18"/>Life, which may bring us back from ſo great a Relapſe: for the which end, it is averred by the Spirit, that there is to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained one continued Act admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of no Ceſſation, as to what may be agreed upon, to have Faith in God; either for <hi>bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> up what hurtful and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious is, to hinder the proceſs or going on of thoſe perfect things yet behind; then again for the <hi>unbinding</hi> and looſning of thoſe mighty, great, and Heavenly Powers that may make us terrible as an invincible bright Army of flying Banners, which as light Flaſhes may go forth, on this Hand, and on that; as directed they ſhall be for the ſecuring, ſaving, and delivering thoſe who ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and mourning are under
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151593:19"/>Sin's oppreſſion, and the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly captivity.</p>
                     <p n="15">§. 15. Now hereupon fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed this Viſion, there being put into my Hand twelve Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and a Bow, the Bow ſeemed to be of pure Gold, and the Arrows tip'd with Gold, and directed I was to make my aim at this Tree of Faith, which was the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rk to ſhoot at. Which keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng my Eye upon ſtedily, the true Archer the Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in me, did let fly one Arrow after another, till I came to the ninth Arrow, which all did well hit: and then there was a ſtop, and I could to no higher degree go; but was commanded to gather up thoſe Arrows and give them into the Hand of them, who were to come up to the Unity of this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151593:19"/>Faith. With the ſame Bow and Arrows, one, who deſigned in ſpecial was, did follow on to try, with great induſtry; and did hit the firſt and ſecond, and then attempting the third De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, the Arrow fell ſomewhat ſhort, for want of a fulneſs of Faith. Whereupon I ſtanding by, directed the holding of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ow, ſo heeding and obſerving well, ſhe reached the third Degree. Then the other one came on to try with the ſame Arrows, appearing in great reſolution, and hit the firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and going upon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond was pulled away, which made a preſent delay. Then did the other that had ſhot to the third Degree, ſtick to it, and after one or two onſets got to the fourth Degree, then ſaw I her ſtop: and it was ſaid,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151593:20"/>Be not hereat diſmayed, for Strength will renew, though the Arm too weak may be, yet lay not down the Bow, but hold it ſteadily, and through conſtant Exerciſe, the Arrow will not fail to fly from the Hand that diligent ſhall be, till it do attain to all Degrees. For it was teſtified unto me, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> there muſt be a continual keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, and bending the Bow of the Mind; that ſo we may all of this Faith's Treaſure find; and although to the Eye of the World nothing of this is ſeen, they looking upon the true Archers of Faith in great deriſion, ſaying, That they are come to be deſperate indeed, that have nothing to live upon but what Faith's Tree muſt bring forth: for ſuch are look'd upon as a forlorn hope. Oh far
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151593:20"/>be it, that this any diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to us ſhould be; for the Lord hath ſaid it again and again, that if any can hereunto reach, &amp; come to an all-full perſwaſion, then the whole World could not contain the Treaſures, which this Tree of Faith for us ſhould command; that ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it may be who are the wiſe in Heart, who have made it their choice to learn, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed be in the Art of Faith only.</p>
                     <p n="16">§ 16. At another time I was alarm'd out of my Sleep with a Voice that cried in me thus, <hi>O the Reſtaurative Tree of Faith!</hi> And when I came to conſider of the Word, and the Meaning of it, Wiſdom's opening Key was put into my Hand, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock that Place where this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151593:21"/>Tree doth ſtand. It did now appear to be encloſed by it ſelf, and a moſt lovely fair Tree it was, the Body whereof ſeemed to be all of ſweet ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Cinnamon, and in the Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of it there was a ſtrong ſcented Perfuming Oil, which did produce Fruit of the ſame Kind, all of a Spicy Nature; the which was ſhewn me to be of Twelve Sorts. But this Fruit appeared different and more various, then what I had ever ſeen in all former Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations. Which made me very Inquiſitive, praying that I might know the Mind of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom in that Surprizing Word, which came ſo ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon me: For I could no way be ſatisfied with any Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or Magical views of things
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151593:21"/>barely, and without Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
                     <p n="17">§. 17. Which through a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed Glance of Light, from her Orb I obtain'd an Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of: And it was thus ſaid to me, O Spirit, what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou here? How doſt thou think to live now that thou art departed out from the Earthly Region, where thy Senſitive Life was maintained through the induſtry of the Rational Mind? From theſe pleaſant Things of the Earth thy Soul is now gone out, and thou muſt eat of them no more: For here is quite another Way and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Living, which thou, and thoſe that are with thee united, muſt faſhion your ſelves unto; living only upon what Fruits this Holy Land, which is by
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151593:22"/>thee now ſeen, doth afford. Therefore did I call thee to come to this Tree of Faith, not only it to view, but, having hit the Mark, thereof to feed; that ſo a Spiritual Body may to thee renewed be, of an Incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible Nature and Kind, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the various ſorts of Fruits, which will reſtore Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to its Antient and Vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Beauty, that hath looked to be altogether withered and conſumed.</p>
                     <p n="18">§. 18. Upon my Further In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry at Wiſdom's Oracle, what might be the Qualities, Properties, and Natures of theſe Fruits of Faith, and how we might be enabled to take of them, having a Right thereto as Natural Denizons, that have a Dependence wholly upon
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151593:22"/>what this Heavenly Country of Immanuel doth afford and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce; that ſo we may have no Occaſion to look back from whence we come, or to be tempted to luſt again after Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Fruits, among the Fallen Spirits. From which ſtate we have been called forth, to live on this Precious Tree of Faith: the ſeveral Properties of which I will now open by Name, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they have been to me declared, to the end that I and thoſe that with me in the ſame Spirit cojoined be, may here ſatisfie our whole Internal Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, and in all Parts and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees be made compleat, as we ſhall hereof Magically in our Spirits be able to eat. Now the Firſt Quality applicable to this TREE is Mageſtical Glory; the Second is Fathomleſs Wiſdom;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151593:23"/>the Third is an Almightineſs of Power; the Fourth is Tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency of Light; the Fifth is Perfection of Purity; the Sixth is Soveraignty of Will; the Seventh is an All-excelling Goodneſs; the Eighth is Infinite Natural Knowledge; the Ninth is an All-ſeeing through the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible Eye; the Tenth is an Eſſential Generating working Spirit; the Eleventh is an Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency of Creation, giving New Exiſtences, where nothing did viſibly appear; the Twelfth is Immutability of Love, which worketh in, and through all theſe. Thus have I given a true Dimenſion, and Deſcription of this Immenſe and Reſtaurative Tree, ſpringing up from the Seed and Root of Faith; which will bring Dead Souls to Life again, and do all the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151593:23"/>Wonders of the New Creation-Church, by the Great <hi>Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phian</hi> Worthies, when they ſhall be made to appear. On it the Firſt begotten Son of Wiſdom did continually feed, which made him a God-Man indeed: who is not contented of theſe unknown Sweet to taſt alone, but cries, and calls, to his Siſter, and his Spouſe hereof with him to partake; that ſo it may have the ſame operation and effect on her, Godlike to be, according to the Pattern of her Lord CHRIST,
<q>
                           <l>Whoſe Image lively drawn I may thus ſee,</l>
                           <l>Through Participation of this <hi>Spicy</hi> Tree.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p n="19">§. 19. Some conſiderable time afterward, I was again call'd in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151593:24"/>Spirit to view this Tree of Faith, and the Tree now ſeem'd to be enlightned with a bright Body, which appeared ſtanding in the midſt of it: and it bore all thoſe ſeveral mentioned ſorts of Fruits, being therewith moſt richly laden, but none were yet Ripe, or fit for Eating. But the Bright Body in the Tree, ſaid; Go, call ſuch as willing are to wait for the Tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Power, to act forth the Amazing Wonders of a God. Let ſuch, with thee, come, and ſit under this Tree, till the Fruit into Gold ye ſhall ſee to be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Then eat thereof ye ſhall, and Power will be born ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to do and act in the Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Nature of the Holy Ghoſt. For this muſt Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute, and alter the whole In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Part; for that it will be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151593:24"/>no leſs then the Leaven of the Deity it ſelf. Whence this hath been frequently repeated to me, that this kind of Power, which we would have, muſt proceed from a deep Ground, and Root; which is no leſs then the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</p>
                     <p n="20">§. 20. Alſo at another time, I felt a mighty ſtirring Life of Faith get up, which did overtop all Self-Reaſoning, whereby I found a Paſs for my Spirit to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nearer ſtill to the Aimed Mark, which is the Central Power. And while I was in Prayer, that my Bow might abide in Strength, and that it might alſo be given to my Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Labourers to hold it out with me, for Aſſurance of this there was ſhewn me the Bow in a Blew Cloud deſcending, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151593:25"/>it was put into my Hand. All Cryſtalline the Bow appeared to be, with Seven Golden Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows belonging to it. Then was it ſaid to me, Ariſe, Ariſe, now put on thy Strength; for the Arm of the LORD, in thee, ſhall ſtretch the Bow, and make the Arrows fly where the Invincible Power doth lie. For the Work ſhall not be ſtarved for want of Power to feed and ſtrengthen it, while two or three do ſtand in one Spirit knit. Therefore to you each one this Bow of Faith is given, with the Sevenfold Arrow: Try, and ſee, whether at the Seventh At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it may not the Power hit, and all the Twelve Degrees of Faith arrive at. Now put thy Hand hereto, and be very nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and quick: make the firſt Onſet, that thoſe others who
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151593:25"/>aiming are at the ſame thing, with thee, may alſo reach this weighty and worthy Prize; That ſo in the Lord ye may rejoice together, in ſuch a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Habitation, and Golden Tent, to celebrate the Praiſe of Great ELOHIM, who hath this Power down ſent to diſplay, and make way for the Gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of his Prieſtly Flock, and Royal Train, that ſhall no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at the Worldy Spirits Gate knock and wait. This came to paſs in the 25th. of the Month <hi>January,</hi> in the Year MDCXC.</p>
                     <p n="21">§. 21. After ſeven Days, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Firſt of the next Month, the ſame Viſion was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed to me, and I ſtrongly felt the Impulſes of the Spirit driving me forward towards the Mark,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151593:26"/>which ſeemed to ſtand very fair to be hit; as inviting us who in One Faith were knit, to try and prove. Where our Seven <hi>Nazarite</hi> Locks of Strength do lie, which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Seven Spirits and Powers of the Tri-Un Deity. For the Seven Arrows ſpecified in the former Viſion do all of this ſignifie, as that theſe are to be a Guard upon each Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, according as from the Bow they ſhall be made to fly. For with my Lord I diſcourſed this matter, concerning the Thorough-Paſs of theſe Seven Arrows, Querying whether I, or any one that principally aim'd at the ſame thing with me, had ſhot them home to the very Center-Point? Then upon this Inquiry the Spirit of my Lord told me, that Five of them had
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151593:26"/>already hit the Mark, but that two yet remain'd; which were to make the grand Breach, and Onſet, where the Rich Prize was to be taken. And the Spirit ſhewed me further what ſtopped the aſcending Might of theſe two remaining Arrows, which was a muddy Gulf that ſtood in the way, which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held: and it was ſaid, That this did ſignifie the Lake of <hi>Self-Reaſoning</hi> Spirits; which the Starry World from Without doth qualifie, with what of Fear and Unbelief is ſtirred up from the World Within us, ſo as the Power could not ariſe ſtrong enough for ſo Great an Enterprize. Wherefore there was all the need that is poſſible of a ſtrong Guard upon theſe that were yet to go out from the Bow, that the Gulf might
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151593:27"/>not ſwallow them up. This was the Counſel given from the Holy Spirit, with this encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging Word, that ſtrength of Omnipotency ſhould attend us, in whatever our Hand ſhall find to do, as we go on to perſue ſo worthy, a noble and God-exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Glory, as the Finiſhing Part will moſt evidently to all Spectators appear to be, when we ſhall come to ſit under Faith's Tree, having through the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Spirit and Power of God arriv'd to all its Twelve De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, there to feaſt upon all its Fruits, and to know the true Banquet and Supper of the Lamb.</p>
                     <p n="22">§. 22. Now turning again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Watch for the Inſpeaking Oracle, to ſatisfie ſeveral Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries which aroſe in me, one of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151593:27"/>which more particularly was with great ſubmitted Humility, an Inquiry <hi>Why the Expected Power of Faith in any one yet could not go forth; albeit ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Promiſes have been Renewed and Repeated upon one, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another of us, that have been kept up ſtill in the Infallible Word?</hi> And it was hereupon Anſwered me thus, ſaying, Do ye think it a light or a ſmall Thing which ye are aiming at? Know this then, for a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Stay to Thee, and to the Waiting Spirits with Thee uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſame Eternal Band, howſoever and whereſoever diſperſed they may be upon the Face of the whole Earth, that there is a Sphere, which muſt be cut through, that ſo the Spirit may paſs to find the Central Power, which this Starry Sphere,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151593:28"/>and Outward Conſtellations do yet ſtop and hinder, who would hold their Dominion ſtill up over the Mortal Man. For if this Circle be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken through by any
<note n="*">See <hi>Enoch. Walks,</hi> p. 39.</note> Mighty Champion, in the Faith of God himſelf, opening in the Soul, then all of that Oppoſing Kingdom falleth: and till then the Kingdom of the Power can have no Place. Therefore fly ye, and get above the Starry Bindings, and all that is of this lower Elementary World: Mount, mount above all the Elements ye Flying Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and ſhoot the laſt and Seventh Golden Arrow, which hath on it the Emblem of an Eye that is all-ſeeing, and two Wings that are over all Gulfs to fly, and ſo to paſs God's ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151593:28"/>Treaſury; then the Power will be ſet free, and effect what each one of you have deſtred ſo exceedingly. This gave for the preſent ſome ſatisfaction to my Spirit, and an Encouragement to preſs forward to the Mark of the High Calling of Faith.</p>
                     <p n="23">§. 23. But having preſſed on, for ſome conſiderable while longer, to this Mark, and being ſtill kept back from it, I have been frequently caſting up my Accounts in the Truſt of the Heavenly things, which have been to me committed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the Thread of my Mortal Day was near ſpun out, it hath often drawn my Mind and Spirit into God, my Deep, for Inquiry to find out, what it is that hath ſo very long kept me from hitting the Mark of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151593:29"/>High Faith, and that hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed the Reigning Life in the Power of the Holy Ghoſt, by one continued Motion and Act from the Deity; that ſo I might know my ſelf to be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into Baptized: being no leſs then what I have been cauſed to Hope, and Believe, that I am to poſſeſs and enjoy, through great Strife, and Soul-Travels tending hereto; as no way to be Pacified, till I had brought forth in me the Mighty Birth of Faith, the Heir of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and the Firſt-born of the Power, Actually and God Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtatively.</p>
                     <p n="24">§. 24. Now as I have been in this Inquiſitive State, and Unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, that I had reached no further with my Arrow, I have ſtill found freſh Manuductions
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151593:29"/>and Encouragements to lead me higher, and nearer to the Laſt and Utmoſt Degree of Faith. But more particularly, while I was, about the middle of <hi>April</hi> in the enſuing Year, thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moaning and lamenting the melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and paſſing away of Time, without any thing of a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>working Power that is ſeen, as it was in the Day of Chriſt, and of the Apoſtles; I had this ſpoke in me from the Only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealer of Secrets. Who in Plainneſs of Speech diſcourſed the matter, and cauſed me to receive right Information con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the with-holding of God's wonderful Appearance throughout Soul, Spirit, and Body. And it was thus made out, that the ſeperation from the corruptible Matter was not yet wrought out, for there was
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151593:30"/>yet a dividing to be, as of the pure from the impure, in the very original Ground and Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Soul. For all is there to be conſumed, which is not clearly of God: and this is to be done by the eternal purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fire, from that one pure Element, which at firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the Eternal Angelical Natures: and as thus it was then, ſo the ſame Motion of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity muſt in the Choſen hereunto be made manifeſt in its reſiding power, which will multiply it ſelf into a Heavenly and New Born Generation: Which will be the fulfilling of the univerſal, and particular Prophecies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Reign of Chriſt in the Spirit. For which now the Trumpet ſoundeth, for the gathering the Tribe of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> to whom the Scepter and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151593:30"/>Ruling Power of the Holy Ghoſt will firſt come, in the waiting and ſeparating Ground-work, as hath been deſcribed by <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi>'s Law-giver: Who hath ſaid that a Body of Virgin-Spirits he will rear up, that ſhall renew his great and mighty Works, which all of former ones are to excell. Therefore ſaid he to me, Go on to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that which remains in the Soul's ground, from which may ſpring that which will multiply Numberleſs Powers.</p>
                     <p n="25">§. 25. Upon which Word of Counſel, great and ſtrong dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings I felt ſtill following me for the very Body of God, which is Chriſt, to be manifeſted in a growing Subſtantiality, from the firſt Eternal Nature, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which Deifick Matter do
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151593:31"/>again ſpring, and feed, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it ſelf by, and from, it ſelf, it cannot otherwiſe live ſeperate, and be free to act and do after its own kind ſuperſenſually. And that it may thus get the upperhand, I was taught here to ſink away from the old Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely Nature, with all its ſenſible Paſſions and Affections; that ſo loſing that Life, I might come to find my Eternal Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Life, from its own Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal to put forth, which is God in a fixed Body, created and brought forth from the firſt Creating Word, which is to reſtore the Lapſe again.</p>
                     <p n="26">§. 26. So that this is the work and buſineſs that my Lord of Life doth ſet before me to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe conſtantly, and is the true meaning of Chriſt's Doctrine
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151593:31"/>of Self-denyal, which teacheth me where lies the Vein of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Blood, that muſt be let out, whereby the precious Life may be ſecured and ſaved; that ſo the Blood of Spirits from God may circulate pure and free. This will renew Incorruption, where the Selfhood of Corruption hath ſo long reigned; for my Lord hath ſaid this to me in ſolemn Verity, henceforth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſee what it is which muſt be diſmiſſed, before ever I can come to ſay God is in the Act of a continued flowing Spring from the Expreſs Deity, paſſing through the Image of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed Chriſt into me, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from all Creaturely Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that are raiſed otherwiſe in the Mind.</p>
                     <p n="27">
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:151593:32"/>§. 27. This is the ſummity of the Everlaſting Goſpel, that ſome Angels, who thus qualified are, ſhall as flying Meſſengers from the Heavens declare: Then ſaid my Spirit, which was taken up into the Lord, Oh who, and where are the Angels of the Power that have prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their Trumpets to ſound? no Tidings of them yet can be heard. No, ſaid my Inſpeaker, they have not yet acquitted their Earthly Tombs, nor put on their Reſurrection Bodies, that ſo they may have boldneſs to be witneſs-bearers to this Goſpel-Revelation, which yet to very few is made known, and but darkly underſtood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there hath not been Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit given to that ſtill Way of the Holy Spirit's infuſion and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151593:32"/>dictation; which requires great heedfulneſs, and an interiour watchfulneſs within the Mind, at all times.</p>
                     <p n="28">§. 28. While thus I was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd with a pleaſant Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Conference in the Spirit with my Lord, I moved on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of a Perſon, Whether or no he might not be deſigned to go forth in this Everlaſting Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Meſſage, as having been a waiter with me for this? And it was Anſwer'd me, It might be his Lot if he could fix to it, and obſerve the Method and Rules now given, not digreſſing or dividing in his Mind, but ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloſe to the One Thing, as gained to it he hath been: for the Miniſtry of the Spirit was a very nice and pure thing, that did require extraordinarily qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151593:33"/>Perſons to ſpeak God forth therein; for if any thing of Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ſhould entervene, it would quench the fiery Lamp of the Spirit, and make it burn weak and dim. This is caution for my ſelf, and Friend, and ſuch alſo who do ſeparate themſelves to this end, to build up an Holy Prieſthood and Tabernacle, in which the Holy Ghoſt may come to Evangelize with a new Spring; which will work away the pudled Matter of every Selfiſh born thing, that hinders the <hi>Live Coal</hi> of the Spirit from Burning.</p>
                     <p n="29">§. 29. Then was I minded alſo of our <hi>Nazarite</hi> Vow, whether or no we had kept to it; for default herein found might keep back the Crown of Anointing, which is, and ever will be the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151593:33"/>true Mark and Character of Chriſt's anointed and moſt Holy Prieſts who are called, within the Vail of the moſt Holy Place ever to attend. There is no go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, to pollute our ſelves with dead and unprofitable things, as we would ſucceed and proſper in this High and Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Profeſſion of Faith, which by holding faſt to, my Lord hath it verified, we ſhall become his anointed Prieſts and Kings, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impowered to work the New Creation-Wonders accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Holy Ghoſt's pure Act and Will in us.</p>
                     <p n="30">§. 30. This is the great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging Motive which the High Throne and Kingly Prieſt doth ſet before us to enkindle freſh Love and Zeal to compleat, what lieth yet imperfected in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151593:34"/>the Ground-work in us for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purification, ſo as paſſing through to the very root Eſſence of the Soul by the Hand of the Separator, whoſe Love Fire it is that cleareth the morſy rough Metal from the Golden Ore, that lieth ſo deeply hid; which O God, is that we would no longer be at a loſs by ſeeking for, and not finding: But through the luſtre of thy ſhine and Glory,
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>We in our ſelves this Golden Deep may find,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Still Watching to the Furnace of our Mind.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:151593:34"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>July</hi> the 26th.</head>
                     <p n="31">§. 31. THe Eternal Word did open it ſelf thus in me, how that the Spirit from this Word of Life, had at ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry times, and diverſly by Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Prophecy been opening the Myſtery of Faith unto me, for the end that I might a skilful Practitioner in it come to be, and now again a <hi>Live Coal</hi> was put into my Hand with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring Breath that I did feel as Wind did blow upon it while I held it in my Hand, ſo as that many Sparks were blown from it. Which obſerving and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring into, it was revealed that thoſe Sparks were the Seeds of Faith that had been already in me ſown, which had
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151593:35"/>for ſeveral Years been putting forth only as Sparks, but the Live Coal it ſelf which is the Root and Body of the Sparks of Faith had not till now been given; the Power, Nature and Quality of which I ſhould well underſtand, for it was deſigned I ſhould ſtill carry it in my Hand to go forth to touch ſuch as called and choſen a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> to wait and live with me, in Love's Burning-Buſh, being thereto invited with my fellow Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers hitherto to turn in, for out of this Flaming Body the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Faith ſhould evidently be ſeen.</p>
                     <p n="32">§. 32. And it was further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noted unto my Intellectual Mind, that God is upon Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſome in ſpecial to be as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elijah,</hi> to act in the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151593:35"/>Spirit of Faith, to deliver as <hi>Moſes</hi> did God's <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of the ſervitude of the oppreſſing <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> Whoſe Spirit in this day doth trouble, moleſt, uſurp, oppreſs, and trample down the Holy People: and no deliverance there will be till the lifted up Standard of Faith's Power ſhall into the Hand of ſome be put: who ſet apart, are to go forth in the Power and Spirit of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah.</hi> The which Manifeſtation of Faith is to be ſet afoot and revived now in this preſent time, for which purpoſe the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of it is renewed.</p>
                     <p n="33">§. 33. The mighty Powers from the Heavens do in me r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> with the mild and ſweet, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> thunder Cries; which from the Heavens I do hear to call, and gather in the diſperſed of the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151593:36"/>Dove Flock, who in Thrall and Bondage have all their days been locked up, that now into Faith's School they may come there to be taught the true An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and Eternal Freedom. Of the which, I ſhall as I my ſelf have been taught by the great Maſter of this Divine Myſtery ſomewhat thereof declare from that Scripture which was brought, and opened unto me, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.22, 23, 24, 25. For being all included under Sin, this brings curſed Miſeries, as Cares, Toils, Sorrows, Fears, Diſtreſſes in Mind, and upon the Soul's ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count alſo Clouds, Doubts and Anxeities. So that both inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and outwardly here is a ſunk deplorable Caſe; and what muſt relieve, and redreſs, and redeem Souls out of all theſe Evils, but Chriſt, who is the ſaving Ark
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151593:36"/>of Faith, giving himſelf to ſuch as can receive him to be the Body, in which the Live Coal of Faith by its Heat produceth vigorons Acts of Faith? Now before this Faith is received, or Chriſt who is the Power and Spring of this Faith; we who were as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law;</hi> Under what Law? even that Law of an Earthly carnal Senſe, that is ever more warring againſt the Law of Faith: and next to this is the Law of Righteouſneſs, which the Apoſtle mentions. And which muſt alſo give place unto the Law of Faith: All Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Works muſt be excluded; for only the Righteouſneſs of Faith muſt here ſtand. Now if we look in, and examine how it hath been with us, we ſhall find we have been in bondage
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151593:37"/>to both theſe Laws, which have carried it very ſeverely towards us. So that before Faith came to be revealed, in what a dark impriſoned Life were we kept? There was no Comfort, nor Satisfaction in all ſtrict Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Law of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, no more then in the Law of Sin and Carnal Senſe; ſo that it is time for us to look out for another Law, which may redeem us out of both theſe: which is this revealed Law of Faith. Which will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a New Birth-Nature, as is mentioned in the 26th Verſe, becoming all the Children of God by Faith in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and ſo Born from the Virgin-Womb of the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>-Mother.</p>
                     <p n="34">§. 34. So that you may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtand the drift of God
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151593:37"/>our Father, is to bring us up in the Faith, from the very Day of our being born into it; ſo that we as little Children muſt learn the Rules of Faith, like as in the firſt and natural Birth we were brought up habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and inherently, in the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional corrupt ſenſibility, and indeed were bound by that Birth, and under the Laws alſo, of righteous Rationality and ſober Senſuality. Which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though good in its kind, and to be obeyed and ſubjected to, till ſuch time as the Royal Birth of Faith comes to be Born: then is to be ſounded the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilee Hour, the Hour and Day of our Releaſe is come, then no longer are we under thoſe Laws which was the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of bondage, curſe, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, heavineſs to Death. From
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151593:38"/>this firſt Husband we are by the Law of Faith ſet free, that ſo we may gradually come up to that <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the <hi>Faith,</hi> as to come to be in great ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty married to him, who is the full Body, Life, and Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Faith; ſo that by this divine Matrimonial Continuity fruitful Births of Faith may be, that may bear the Name of God's Angelical Hoſts; For none elſe can ever be capable to do the great Works and Wonders which are to be manifeſted in him, while under the covert of a Mortal form: but ſuch as have the Live Coal of Faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in their Hearts, and put into their Hands, whereby they may go forth to tincture and to touch, and leaven from the Vertue, of the central Marriage-Union, which may bring forth
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151593:38"/>the flaming or blown-up-Coal of the Holy Ghoſt, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the Birth of Faith doth precede as a Forerunner. By which all Miracles may then moſt eaſily be wrought, which muſt the laſt redeeming part of Mankind clear up and finiſh. For all Dominions and Powers in the Worlds of Death, Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Wars and Strife ſhall and muſt evidently, by the Holy Ghoſt in Faith's Power and Might be put under and to flight: Even ſo let it be in Faith's Spirit pray we.</p>
                     <p n="35">§. 35. Waiting further in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit upon this High Matter, the Oracle of Witneſs again open'd in me after Three Days, and it ſaid: Go forward, &amp; do not ſlack to promote, and to draw forth for an United Body, in the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151593:39"/>Faith together to ſtand. For hereunto are ye called, to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and Believe in the One only Saving Name JESUS: and ſuch as with thee ſo ſhall avouch the Everlaſting God their God only to be, the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of Faith upon their Heads ſhall flow. Then hold forth do ye mutually a clear Teſtimony hereof, by giving up your ſelves in way of Pure Seperation, as in a Silent Wilderneſs, there to attend, for what is yet to come from the Seven Fountain Throne Spirits: Which way being to light ſuch Precious and Unut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable Things, as have been kept from all vulgar ſight. Therefore I ſay in Faith's Tent together abide, and to no other Buſineſs your Minds apply, that ſo a Praiſe ye may be to <hi>Elohim</hi> Great; who will aſſuredly own
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151593:39"/>and ſtand by you, in the Work he hath appointed you to: which followed is to be cloſe, and uninterruptedly. O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Courage take, my Called and Anointed Ones, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by raiſe up ye may that Glory, which under a Cloud of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy hath lain: and withal count it all Joy, that ye who thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed are together, to ſee and obtain that high Love-Prize, which others have negligently loſt, and which a warning may be to hold out, and to Conquer the Temptations of a Mortal State.</p>
                     <p n="36">§. 36. As this Word came in, the Figure of a Crown was lifted up upon the end of a Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which caſt from it a Glance of Tranſparency of Glory. And then the Word came anew, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151593:40"/>ſaid: Behold, and ſee, this ſhall be the Reward of Unwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Waiters in the Faith, who for a Kingdom are ſeeking, and deſerting all Viſibles. Such as theſe who ſeek out and wait Believingly, and who through this Belief are made to forſake all, ſhall come infallibly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit, and poſteſs the Scepter and the Crown, with CHRIST their Head Prince of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. Wherefore gird up ye who are Lovers of, and Wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for, the Lamb's victorious Day, to be revealed in you; that ſo glorious Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives in his Life ye may come to be, in the Kingdom of Conqueſt and Victory. The which hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out to, ſhall and will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dear you to the Heart of your God and Father actually, who hath waited for to ſee, who ſo
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151593:40"/>Valiant could be, as to break through every Cloud of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and in no wiſe be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented of the great Felicity, which by this Victory of Faith is to be.</p>
                     <p n="37">§. 37. Then was I for ſome time afterward followed ſtill with this Word, ſaying: Fear not, but go on to perform what hath been in the Platform pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> to thy Mind. For the Heart of thy God will ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and cojoin ſuch with thee, as of a <hi>Gideon</hi>-Might and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit approved are in Valiantneſs, for that which undertaken is now to be. Thus having been encouraged to ſtand up unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably in that Faith, which is of Divine Operation, and not to be afraid in the leaſt, or waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Belief of the Promiſes,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151593:41"/>which have been given of Old Times, and which have power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully been renewed to me; I have been made to haſten from one Degree of Faith to another, and to ſhoot continually Arrow after, that ſo at laſt I might obtain the Prize, by aiming at the Unity of it, in hitting the Point which for theſe many Years I have been Aiming at.</p>
                     <p n="38">§. 38. Thus having r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ved Line upon Line, and Prophecy upon Prophecy, for my Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, I was ſtill upon the moſt inward Debate with the Lord Chriſt, or rather with his Agent the Spirit, why the Word of Revelation and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the Prophetical Senſe opened, ſhould not be attended with Miraculous working Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? For, indeed, that is the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151593:41"/>great Thing that the Myſtery of Faith moves hard for, namely to bring the Eternal Working Properties to Fix again in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's inward ground. Againſt which all the Earthly Senſes conſpire to reſiſt, continually raiſing up Blocks of Unbelief; which hath been the one great Cauſe of Reſtraint, as we in God's Light do underſtand.</p>
                     <p n="39">§, 39. But it was ſaid to me by the Word of the Lord, that theſe great mighty Working Powers, that the whole Courſe of the Viſible Reign in the Earth would change, could not be intruſted with any till God becomes Man, and Man becomes God, all throughout in a diſtinct Perſonality, as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Manner of our Lord JESUS. To which eſtate we
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151593:42"/>are to be Redeemed, that ſo we may come into a Joint Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in the Kingdom, which is all Power.</p>
                     <p n="40">§. 40. For this was the very Word that was given me, Be not ſolicitous for Almighty working Power, till the Deity hath wrought out Mens groſs Eſſence, that from the Mortal Birth doth ſpring, and reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed all anew, by pouring in his Baptizing Name, which will the Seal of the Power again engravve. For the Gifts and Powers no more given out will be, till a Fixed Body be all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated with Ingredients pure from the Celeſtial Orb. Which ſaid the Word, Ye ſhall do well to Believe, and make all Haſt after this Hope to purſue it: for it hath its Seaſon to be fulfilled.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:151593:42"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>June</hi> 6. 1691.</head>
                     <p n="41">§. 41. THis Morning I felt the Spirit opening further unto me the Myſtery of Faith, of the which I have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded much for my own Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Improvement: but this Day much more hath been Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, out of the deepeſt Ground from its Eternal Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginality, God abſtractedly; which in a moſt full Body opens in me, like as in all its Uſeful Members. Now the Birth of Faith is on this wiſe ſhewed to be, full of Life, Motion, and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity: yet all whatever it work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and doth, is after an hidden and ſilent way. Foras the out ward Man hath all in a Viſibility to exerciſe his Original Faculties upon, ſo contrariwiſe doth this Spirit of Faith, put forth
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:151593:43"/>all its Powers, and Spiritual Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuities moſt effectually after a Secret Inviſible Manner: and effecteth that which it aimeth at, though no outward Speech or Noiſe of Words may be here needed, nor viſible Hands to work, or Feet to walk; but all lieth hidden in the deep Center of a Pure Mind, which works and performs Great Things on this Hand, and on the other, and yet no Vulgar Corporeal Being can the ground of this way of working find out, or diſcern. It is only known by the Operator, who can Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentally tell, that it is No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs then what doth lie as Deep as God, there Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porating with the Soul, and going forth with pure Acts of Power.</p>
                     <p n="42">
                        <pb n="79" facs="tcp:151593:43"/>§ 42. This Opening and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation concerning the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Faith; hath been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to me as the Magical Key, which openeth the ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>up Wonders of God's Eternity. Now my Buſineſs is to handle, and employ This Key, as skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and inſtructed I ſhall be from my Tutereſs the Supream Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who hath ſhewn, and brought me to her ſeveral Gates; and hath given forth to every Gate a diſtinct Key, for the Opening One Deep upon another: Whereinto my Spirit is to paſs, which now call'd forth afreſh I am to follow. For well ſatisfied I am, that the Bright Star a Conduct will to me aſſuredly be, and ariſe ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, after ſome Years delay, which had made me ready to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151593:44"/>give up the Ghoſt of my Hope, in reference to that which in Divine Wiſdom's Glaſs I have ſeen, heard, and underſtood, concerning what in my Day is to be Accompliſhed, and brought into Effect.</p>
                     <p n="43">§. 43. But at this time the Power beginneth mightily to ſtir, and the Virgin-Tincture of the pure Spirit of Wiſdom, doth in my Spiritual Veins run, that the Revealed Things may into an Heavenly Body turn. For I now do ſee, and find a Body to its fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l grown Stature prepared is to be, in wonderful Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, till every Organ, Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and Faculty be run through with the higheſt Vertue from the Deity. This my Lord in the Spirit did tell me, bidding me patiently to abide, until this
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151593:44"/>true <hi>Shilo.</hi> Body in me was to its full heighth ſhot up; for that then ſhould the moſt Power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Glorious, Holy Ghoſt, appear to do and act his Part: and after ſuch a long Silence even in the very Heavens, ſhould then Speak through me, not by Voice only, but by pure Act. O this is the Proof that my God will of himſelf give, when being thus filled with Him, Deeds from a Deified Power and Root ſhall ſpring up and manifeſt themſelves. Some Workings in order to this I do already ſenſibly feel, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore encouraged I am to wait, and to give all place for the Fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of this Holy Being, which will nullify all other Beings; that ſo entirely I may poſſeſs the Great JEHOVAH<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as my Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, continually within to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151593:45"/>flow, for the waſhing away of the Impurities, and for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring a Body in which the Holy Ghoſt ſo Fixedly may dwell, as never out of it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part away.</p>
                     <p n="44">§. 44. Some ſhort time after this the Manifold Wiſdom did again open it ſelf in me, for my further Information, that ſo I might hit the Mark, which I have been ſo longing for, and aiming at. Now that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> might be right ſet in my Way, the Spirit and Bride gave me not only a Call, but a Love-enforcing Pull, from all that is of this low Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Aſtral Life; and ſo up my Spirit was preſently Caught to underſtand, and learn, what was to be expreſly wrought by the Superceleſtial Art, from which Altogether is
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151593:45"/>excluded the outward Hand of Craft.</p>
                     <p n="45">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 45. Now the Copy I was to learn by, was that Original Word that was from Eternity; which by entring, or opening it ſelf in that Part which purely doth relate to God, ſimply, and abſtractedly from the Lower Rational Conſubſiſtency, that is from the Outward Elements. For all of this ſort muſt be laid aſide in this way of Work<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, which is after the Manner of him, who hath the Creating Power and Principle, for giving a Life, and Exiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy out of Nothing. This is the Celeſtial School which I am ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into, in order to be brought up according to the Degree of my Eternal Nativity; which I am driving to run back again
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151593:46"/>unto, that ſo I might under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how to Act from this Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Port, even from the Centre of a New Heart, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pon which may be written that great Name <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega.</hi> Which only can renew the Working Power, that ſhall the Seal'd Teſtimony open, and get thereby the Crown of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, to enter upon the Lord <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Kingly Reign within the circle of the pure Mind; and from thence to go forth to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern in all parts without, till the Wonders of God ſhall as Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fly out, upon the Eagle-Wings of Faith: and the Fruits of this <hi>TREE,</hi> ſpringing up in the Paradiſical Ground of the Soul, ſo plentifully drop, as to convert the howling De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of this outward Mortal Principle into a pleaſant <hi>Sharon,</hi>
                        <pb n="85" facs="tcp:151593:46"/>and <hi>Eden</hi> of God. This for certain is the only thing, that will bring the long expected Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption to its finiſhing End.</p>
                     <p n="46">§. 46. After which, as from a New Guſt, the Eternal Word open'd it ſelf Expreſly in my Heart's Center, informing and declaring the High Prerogative of ſuch a Spirit, in whom the Power of Tranſmutation did lie. For in whom ever this comes to be witneſſed, it is no leſs then the Seed of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, retained in the pure Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix of the Virgin Wiſdom, which driveth forth, till it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into Tranſubſtantiation. Nothing goeth beyond this, for as much as it is the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Strength, Might, and Excellency of the Father of all Spirits, who generateth in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151593:47"/>this High Birth of Power, the true Heir of Faith, as it did appear in the Immaculate <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi> How great is this Secret, and to whom hath it been Revealed? or who hath found this Wonderful Stone? True it is, that in all Ages it hath had its Seekers: but none have digged deep enough for it. Every Arm for theſe many Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years hath been too ſhort to reach it. Now unto thee, who art duly upon the Inquiry, and watching for the highly precious Gate to open, while thou art knowing in thy ſelf the Invalidity of all other forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Births and Powers: that yet have been reſted upon, as if this had been attained to, which thou art now preſſing to find within the Borders of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel, where the Seven Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151593:47"/>Pools are to be paſſed through, before this Tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Stone comes to its perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Colour. And though ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of them thou haſt been plunged into, yet know this that there remain Three. Which were ſhewn me to be Blood, Oil, and Fire. The Four that I had paſſed through were, <hi>firſt</hi> the Pool of Conviction; <hi>ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> Repentance; <hi>thirdly,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation; <hi>fourthly,</hi> paſſing my Spirit over by pure Dedication. By all which I was made meet to enter upon the laſt Three Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſms, which would finiſh the whole Myſtery of the Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Bloody Pool is the Dying with JESUS, the Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up thy ſelf through his Spirit: to which end the many Lives are to ſuffer Death with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pity, or ſparing any one of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:151593:48"/>them, as they were allied, and in concord, with the ſenſitive Root, from whence they all do ſpring, haply thou mayeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve thy ſelf to have paſs'd through every Death. I grant that thou haſt done ſo in thy Will; yet art thou not come to an actual, open, and Triumphant ſhew hereof, perfectly ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring, as to a Total giving up the Ghoſt of that Birth, which was out of the Womb of that, which was from the Earth earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and into which it muſt be again delivered up through Death. Now no more would I have thee to draw any Breath of Life, from that Principle which is the Gulf of Seperation: but to paſs undauntedly through this Pool of Blood, which is the Fifth Cirling Pool that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounds that Wonderful Tree of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151593:48"/>Faith, and Life, which thou haſt ſeen.</p>
                     <p n="47">§. 47. Now having after ſome Years preſſing forward, ſince this laſt Manifeſtation, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through theſe Deaths in a good Degree, as hath been witneſſed; the Lamb having been ſlain in me, gives a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of a New Life, which ſtandeth clearly out of all that is of the Out-Birth, and that conſiſteth of the Aſtral Reaſon and Animal Senſe, which the being dead to gains the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Conqueſt, that maketh way for the being plunged into the Pool of Oil. Which Oil is the Matter and Eſſence from which the Holy Ghoſt doth ſpring. Then paſſing from this to the Pool of Fire, which alſo opens it ſelf from this, being a Fiery
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151593:49"/>Seed from the Deity, and ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulating together, it makes up a Deified Body, which only can be capable to live in the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celeſtial Air of the One Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This we may entitle the Divine Magical Body, whoſe Motions and Operations are all ſubſiſting, &amp; going forth in pure Acts of Faith. For that is the Life that the Riſen in Chriſt are called to, to live by alone; for as much as by this they are always aſcending above the Earth, as if they had no more to do with it; bringing down by Faith all needful Things out of the Store-houſe of Heaven, while yet they are in Bodies Terreſtrial. Our Spiritual Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizing is only to be upon the Fruits of Faith's Tree, which will bring in both for Food and Cloathing abundantly, while
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151593:49"/>there is need for it. But there is an Age coming, as this Tree of Faith grows up in Perſons in their inward ground to its full ripeneſs, when the Fruit being eaten thereof Magically, will Transfigure the very Elementary. Body, and give it a Radical Ruby Glory; ſo that Mortality ſhall be hid in Immortality; which is the Garment that may laſt the Thouſand Years Reign of CHRIST; and may be ſaid to be the Firſt Reſurrection Body, whereby Death ſhall be ſwallowed up. All this will be effected by the Mighty Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faith, which ſubdueth all things to it ſelf, and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth this viſible Body into the Likeneſs of the Glorious Body of our Lord JESUS. For when this Faith ſhall be wrought up to its higheſt Perfection, it
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151593:50"/>will be ſuch a Proſpective-Glaſs, through which the Glorified Perſon of our Lord, and the Father in him, with the Virgin Wiſdom, and all the Saints, ſhall ſo appear before the Spirit's Eye; that according as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, beholding the Glory of the Lord as in Glaſs, we ſhall be changed from Glory to Glory: for when we ſee him, we ſhall be made like unto him. Thus hath it been ſhewn to me, what the wonderful Effects of Faith ſhall do in its Time and Age. But it may be ſaid, who ſhall live ſuch an Age as this to ſee? To which I Anſwer, though this be Propheſied in me, yet it is not Determinated, whether as to my own Particular I may it in my Age of Time ſee. For I rather think that I may paſs into Faith's Myſtery, where
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:151593:50"/>with the High VVorthies of Faith, who <hi>died in the Faith, not having received the Promiſe,</hi> but ſeeing it afar off, rejoyced in Spirit, as I do, hoping that others in the ſucceeding Age, or Ages, may this Transformation of Bodies know: which Joy will be ſo to me, when I into the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly World tranſlated ſhall be, having put on Glorification which I do now already ſee my Superior Angel in the <hi>Mount Sion</hi> Kingdom cloathed withal; in which my Reſt and Satisfaction, in aſſurance hereof, do remain, not knowing whether it may not be my Lot with the Elders and Worthies of the Faith, to deſcend with CHRIST again, upon the Earth to Reign.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:151593:51"/>
                     <head>The 4th of <hi>January,</hi> 169— <hi>A Continuation of what further hereupon followed.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="48">§ 48. THis divine Opening was with me, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me in converſe for ſome Hours in my Spirit, ſaying, Though the ſtaff of Time for an expected deliverance ſeemeth to be broke, yet caſt not off the work you are called to, abide and ſtand together in, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it is the prerogative of God to change Times and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who under no bounds of Time will be, that his depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Creatures may never be off on their Knees as to Prayer and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151593:51"/>watchfulneſs. Then after ſome large Conference with the Spirit, which cannot be brought forth in words, There was preſented to me in ſight a wonderful great Wheel, which ſeemed to ſpread over the whole Earth, the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour was as a Ruby-Red, and it was full of Eyes round the circle of it very piercing: Then it was ſaid to me, This preſents God the Almighty working Wheel, of which there is no beginning or end, ſo I ſaw a living Spirit mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the Wheel, hoiſted up as between the Heavens and the Earth; then ſaw I four ſmall Wheels deſcend out of this, one of the ſame colour, and had Eyes alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then I enquired, Ah Lord, tell me what this mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth? And it was anſwered, Theſe are the Charriot-Powers which paſs through all things
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151593:52"/>in Centers high and Centers low, and to whom theſe Wheels ſhall be joined unto, they only ſhall be able to act the great Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of time; then ſaw I where they deſcended and reſted for a while: and then they went forth and were lifted up by the great Wheel, which as a Loadſtone drew them up, and my Spirit was preſently gone to them, and preſently the Angelical Center ſtood open, and from thence my Spirit was carried by theſe Wheels into the Apoſtles Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then into the Son's Center, then into the Father's deepeſt deep of all Centers, where I was to center and abide till the Wheels went forth, then my Spirit ſhould go with them, who would be Eyes to ſee what way and whither my Spirit was to go, do, and act, for it was ſaid
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151593:52"/>to me, Now no Creaturely Will can move here; for the Holy Spirit aſſumeth all Will, Power and Act here, and then no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat is to the high, holy, pure Enterprize, which you together in the Faith and Love co-work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with theſe Wheels, it ſhall be as the ſpreading of the Net aright, and caſting it, to the taking of a worthy and rich Prize: ſo go forward on and proſper.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>February</hi> 10. 1694.</head>
                     <p n="49">§. 49. This Morning the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Four Wheels ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared again, which moved in the Four Elements; each one being carried upward by a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that was as a bright Flaſh of Lightning. The which conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151593:53"/>in my Mind, with an inquiry hereupon made, it was told me, That they did repreſent the working Wheels of Nature, that the All-powerful Spirit doth drive upward to reach the One Eternal Element; which being touched with it, would penetrate through the whole Bodily Man, that was made up of the Four Elements. Then did I ſee theſe Four Elements expire into one great terrible Flaming Wheel, that ſpread it ſelf over the whole Heavens: and in the middle of the VVheel there were Seven Eyes.</p>
                     <p n="50">§. 50. Which I waiting upon was thus opened to me, that the groſs Earthly Part in the nature of the Four Elements, ſhould by the Spirit of Chriſt, who took upon him the Elementary
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151593:53"/>Body, ſo come into ours, as to wind them up by a ſtrong Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cling Motion, as every Part may be ſo touched, as to be tinged with, and to partake of the Superiour Properties and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of this pure and unmixed Element; and ſo be ſwallowed up in this Great Governing Wheel, that ruleth over all the lower Wheels, with all the Planets, which thereto do coagulare and work. For all by Outward Nature are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Power, and Empire, till got free, by aſcending up to this upper ruling Wheel, with its Seven Eyes: Concerning which it was told me, that they were the Seven Superceleſtial Planets, or Conſtellations, that did govern and controll all in this lower World, and its Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets. This is that which will
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151593:54"/>reach to Redemption of the Body.</p>
                     <p n="51">§. 51. Much more the Spirit of my Lord diſcourſed me up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Matter, which muſt be concealed till my Outward Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Wheels ſhall fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire into the upper and ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Wheel. Only this I may declare for the preſent time, that the upper Flaming Wheel with its Seven Eyes, as a Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, is drawing mightily, ſome known to me, that have been touched therewith. And it will not reſt in its wheeling Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, till they ſhall be, as to their weak Elementary Life, changed into the One Superiour Element; whereby the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Conſtellations ſhall predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate over all of theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151593:54"/>Ones, which hitherto have reigned over the Elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Part, that yet lieth Unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>February</hi> the 12th.</head>
                     <p n="52">§. 52. This Day being much drawn inward in the Spirit of my Mind, this word met me: Ariſe, and ride upon the Mule of Faith: ſtand over all that is Elementary. There is a Thing to be done by ſome, that in the Crown Number do ſtand; who ſhall the Land of <hi>Havilah</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: but <hi>Abraham</hi>'s High Faith for this muſt ſpring.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:151593:55"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>February</hi> the 14th.</head>
                     <p n="53">§. 53. VVhile I was in a deep Introverſion about this Matter, this Word ſpake in me, ſaying; There is a Birth that is upon breaking forth, that ſhall bring the Bleſſing of mighty Increaſe to preſent, and ſucceeding Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations. <hi>Sarah</hi> in her Old Age is near her time of bringing forth the Heir, who muſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the good things of the Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Neather World. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand thou then what this meaneth: the Old Age is an arrivement unto the Myſtery of Faith. Now excite thou thoſe that are of Good will, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage themſelves with the Hope this good Old Age to ſee, as mighty Hero's in this Faith;
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151593:55"/>that ſo ye may bring forth the Bleſſing to the weary and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. Gird up, I ſay, and take heed ye do not falter, or turn out of Faith's way: then ſhall ye bring forth a Nation as in One Day.</p>
                     <p n="54">§. 54. Now as ſome of us were hereupon waiting together, and while one was in Prayer, there appeared this Viſion from the Light World. From the which the Virgin deſcended, and met an aſcending Spirit, that was preſſing and expecting to come up to the <hi>Mount Sion</hi> Orb, unto the Glorious Lord. But there was a ſtop by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent of the Virgin of that Orb, who appeared to us in great ſplendour, and congratulated us, ſaying: Thus I know where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ye would in your Spirits have
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151593:56"/>arrived, but I am come from your Lord, to make known the Thing which ye have long been in travail for. And now I do appear to you for this purpoſe, that you may be overſhadowed with my Virgin Nature; which may be the Womb all ſanctified for the conceiving of the Holy Ghoſt, which will be the Lordly Birth in Spirit. And as he was brought forth in the Fulneſs of Time, by a ſingle Perſonal Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, ſo now in Plurality in Virgin Spirits, to multiply upon the Earth; that ſo Evil Births may ſink and dye, as theſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Births ſhall riſe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to you, who in holy Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation are, this Counſel is given: Obſerve from this Day, how this Birth in you ſhall go forward on; and therefore watchful each one of you be. And after this Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151593:56"/>ſhe caſt a wonderful bright ſhining Ray of Glory, as we were ſitting together, upon each of us.</p>
                     <p n="55">§. 55. Now at her firſt Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtood with her, and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> that brought forth <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that attended her, giving audience to what ſhe ſpake, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving great Reverence to her. So then ſhe diſappeared. And the next Morning my Spirit cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all this up into my Mind, ſhe appeared again, and asked me whether I had Faith to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what ſhe had made known? For by Faith (ſaid ſhe) your ſtrength will be to Conceive this Lord of Life. At which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſaid, I will their Aſſiſtant be: the Faith that was Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151593:57"/>to me, ſhall cowork mightily in the Spirit that willeth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Then ſhe ſaid, It plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth me well you ſhould their Helper in this Travelling Birth be, till to Perfection it, may come. Then I was made to Query, What we ſhould do fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in order to this thing? And ſhe ſaid, Only <hi>Believe</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> as with One Soul and Heart. then the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> appeared, and he ſaid, The Love which was begotten in me, I will in the way of the Spirit enter, to beget in them, who for this great Thing are appointed, that Love may the cheriſhing of this Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Birth be, to carry it on till the place of breaking forth ſhall be found. Then the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Peter</hi> he appeared with great Amity, and ſaid to me, The Key was given to him to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151593:57"/>Unlock the Centre-pure of this Holy Birth: the Binding alſo is given, ſaid he, to me; and the Evil Eye ſhall under a Tye be. The Looſening Power for the bringing forth hereof, ſhall to the Virgin Minds by me all free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be contributed; to effect what the Princely Virgin hath ſo graciouſly declared. Then being filled with a ſweet ſilent Peace and Joy, as lying in a rich Bath of Flaming Love they withdrew. There were nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Virgins in great Triumph, with the Superiour and Chief One as her Attendants. This further is to be noted, that as I was conſidering ſtill in my mind and watching hereupon, out there went before me Seven bright Stars, and a Crown over them. And enquiring what that ſignified, it was opened in me,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151593:58"/>that they were the Super-Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Planets that Rule, and were to Qualifie with the holy Birth: and that the Crown denoted a King was to be born, and all Dominion and Power ſhould be given to him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>July</hi> the 18th.</head>
                     <p n="56">§ 56. There appeared to me a Glorious Face circled as with a Rainbow: the Face ſent forth ſuch a Reflection of Light, that it drew, as out of a Cloud, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Face, which was as the Likeneſs or Figure of my own Face. Which received ſuch a Bright Glance, as preſently brought up ſeveral, who faced the Face of the ſupream Glory. And many that lay ſtill hid in the Clouds, came one after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151593:58"/>as the Clouds broke away. And by the ſtreaming Light of the firſt preſented Face, we all, as in a Glaſs, did behold the ſhining Glory, that was upon all our own Faces, ſuch of us as in the waiting Life cojoined were.</p>
                     <p n="57">§. 57. Waiting the next Morning, and praying for the Viſion to be made out more to me, that ſo I might underſtand the drift of the Spirit hereby, finding a vehement going out of my mind and deſire after this Face to behold it again; it did accordingly again appear. And then I did not only ſee it, but heard the Voice, ſaying, Thus the ſtrong ardency of thy Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſire hath opened my Face again, to let thee know I will make thee a Head-Leader of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151593:59"/>an Heavenly Train, that ſhall to me their whole Minds, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and Perſons give up for a great and peculiar Work; which hitherto hath lain under a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſpe. Which now gird up to thou, with thy fellow-workers and waiters in the Faith, that have offered themſelves up all willingly hereunto: for my Face and Countenance ſhall be turned ſtill toward you, for the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away thoſe Clouds, that a covering upon the Faces of my choſen Veſſels have been. Thus did the Lord commune with me, who, as the ſmall Duſt of the Ballance ſees her ſelf to be; yet muſt ſtand in a Service for the Lord all obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently; who hath promiſed to be the Hands of Sufficiency, to bring to paſs the great Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders out of the Sea of Glaſs:
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151593:59"/>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>That ſhall theſe Gather'd Faces bleſs,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>With Floods of Joy and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>July</hi> the 23d.</head>
                     <p n="58">§. 58. Being ſtill upon my Watch, for what was further to be Revealed, reſolving to draw off from all the Dregs and Lees of ſenſible Operations, and launch ſtill deeper into the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe Deity: which thus did further open a ſight in me of an encloſed Principle, whoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence was a circling Flame. And within it there appeared bright Beryl Bodies walking up and down, and with them did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as in a Looking glaſs, like as a round Globe, the Perſonal
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151593:60"/>Glory of our Mighty King, who moved as they moved. The Ground they went upon, was paved as with Sparkling Stones, with Veins of Gold, which caſt forth a mighty Luſtre. This all precious and amazing ſight in Spirit given me, moved to an Inquiry, What was to be learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and underſtood?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>July</hi> the 24th.</head>
                     <p n="59">§. 59. So next Morning at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending this Viſion, it was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to the Eye of my Mind ſtill, and Intelligence came in all ſatisfyingly, that this enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Principle was the Land of all Bleſſed Stores, where the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Springing Mines are, that no one could ever come in to ſee and poſſeſs, but ſuch as had
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:151593:60"/>Faced the glorious Face of CHRIST in Righteouſneſs: then added to ſuch ſhould be, the like Beryl Bodies as here I did ſee.</p>
                     <p n="60">§. 60. Then did I make a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inquiry, Whether or no I might, with any other whom I would recommend to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs and Head-Governeſs, here admittance have? And it was Anſwered, That for this very cauſe it was thus by way of proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſhewn unto me; whereby I might underſtand there was a poſſibility for entring in, with ſuch who in the Spirit of Faith's Purity, ſhould be me preſented be here to come, that we might put on our B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ryl Bodies; as burning Saphirs to walk, and talk with him, who in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Globe of Glory here was
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151593:61"/>ſeen. Then upon this feeding my Mind with a pleaſing Hopes of finding entrance here, for my ſelf and ſuch who in Faith's Unity do ſtand, this Word ſpake all powerfully: Haſten to put on you Flaming Garments, then free paſs will for you be, the Flaming Wall parted for you ſhall be: the Governour of this Principle doth both love and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire your Appearance here, for which end he doth appear.</p>
                     <p n="61">§. 61. So retiring ſtill in my Mind, and caſting up theſe Love-Viſitations and Repreſentations, which took up my thoughts, moving the Spirit for further In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, what this Principle might be called, with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants hereof; After ſome ſtillneſs and attendance here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, the Revelation opened
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151593:61"/>in me, and I knew it to be Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom's Orb, or Principle. The Inhabitants herein were all high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arted and skilful in Magical Operations: that is, whatever they bent their Will to do, it was produced and brought forth. So as it was ſhewed me they were exerciſed in ſuch Faith, that whatever they Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in the Eſſential <hi>Chriſt</hi> Conſubſiſting in themſelves, they thereby could accompliſh either for themſelves or for others: even whatever they would that lay within the Circumference of what was either Viſible or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, in God's whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And the Spirit of my JESUS did further again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form me, that my Lord did open this Principle to me, that I with ſuch who in one pureneſs of Spirit could joinedly come to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:151593:62"/>be, might admittance have into this encircled Principle: where Learned we might be in Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom's divine Arts, thereby to free us from the Worldly Crafts.</p>
                     <p n="62">§. 62. Now then know this is a Propheſy, that muſt reach to the Wiſe Men of the Eaſt, who have been hid in Obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet known you are to be Wiſdom's Divine Magicians, that are made skilful to act the mighty Deeds of our Great <hi>Jehovah</hi> Prince. Think not that ye are now much longer to lie hid, for there is an Holy Dove which hath into your Land taken her flight, and with her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Eyes hath you deſcribed, who in her Bill doth carry the Golden Egg, wherein lies the Deep Philoſophy, that muſt multiply ſuch a Treaſury, that
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151593:62"/>muſt ſet the Embondaged free, that from the Earth they may redeemed be, and bear the Name of their God upon their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. For the Diſpenſation of the Fulneſs of Time is now already come, and the Fruits upon the Tree of Faith do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelves ruddy, ſhewing that they are come to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity. Therefore now Alarm'd the mighty Archers are from all their Obſcure Corners to come, that we may now ſee upon whom the Lot may fall, to hit the Mark, and compleat what was lacking of the Number Twelve, that ſo through all Wiſdom's Gates we may paſs, then we ſhall ſtand upon the Sea of Glaſs in. Triumphant Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory the Reign of Chriſt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim, that ſo as Kings, Prieſts and Prophets upon the Earth,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151593:63"/>and over the Earth, we may repreſent him, then will the Tri-Un Deity ſhine forth moſt radiantly, to convey its power through ſimple, weak, poor Corporeities, which though outwardly ſo contemptible are, yet by this Golden Stone of Wonders, which out of the Dove's Bill doth fall, capable may be to put on Bodies of Tranſparency, which will well agree with the high Aſſembly, that with Chriſt in Heavenly places do ſtand, that ſo the mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Reign of the Saints above may be Joined concurribly with thoſe below; and that that which is Above; and that which is Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath may be one glorious Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation for the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Jacob,</hi> This new Prophetical Sound that now doth go forth, is to call and gather in the whole
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151593:63"/>Kingly and Prieſtly Hoſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſcattered and hidden they be; for Wiſdom's Star will be their Conduct to the Second Birth of our Great <hi>Immanuel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="63">§. 63. But now Queried it may be, <hi>Where is the Place that we are to reſort to,</hi> this Kingly Birth to ſee? There are a few Names that linked are in the Golden Chain of Love, and wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are in the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which is from Above, looking for this bleſſed Hope that may open in the Power of the Holy Ghoſt, whoſe burning Breath with freſh ſtrong Odours and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes are blown up, as that the ſcent and favour hereof may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the high Elders of Wiſdom, for the making up the true Sophia Bride, that hath for a while lain conceal'd, but now is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151593:64"/>this being the Fulneſs of Time, in which the ſounding of the Seventh Angel doth her Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with the Lamb proclaim.</p>
                     <p n="64">§. 64. Haſte therefore, O haſte and fly ye Holy Doves from all parts to this <hi>TREE</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> which will afford and make up a Feaſt of all Variety, to entertain you at your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: where the New Wine from the new born Vine will run ſo free, of which we may not only drink our fill, but alſo be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed therein, ſo as thence to appear in the Ruby Tincture, all glorious without, as well as within. This is the Meſſage that I have to declare: Hearken, hearken unto it, for it is to the Love-Kingdom ye are called; which being obedient unto, ye ſhall know that God will be to
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:151593:64"/>you an everlaſting Triumphant Joy.</p>
                     <p n="65">§. 65. O <hi>England, England,</hi> underſtand the Day of thy Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, for this is the Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Year, in which there is a mighty Star that in thy <hi>Bethle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem</hi> City is born, that calleth the Ranſomed Ones from all Nations, Languages, and Tribes, to come to the Brightneſs of its Riſing. Take care, O <hi>England,</hi> leſt this Star do from thee glide away: let not the Clouds of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Suſpicion or demurring Jealouſie, concerning the true Heir of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who is now to enter upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Reign, and to rule with the Scepter of Faith, hinder thee from diſcerning that the Glaſs is now turn'd up, that its <hi>Half Hour</hi> is running, that the third
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:151593:65"/>Watch is ſet, and that the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Cock is thereupon clapping his Wings, and crowing the third and laſt time. Warned therefore ye are, O <hi>Engliſh</hi> Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, that ye do not miſs this your Day, and ſuffer other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions more watchful and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to this Call, to take the Birth-right from you, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant you off of your Crown. This Alarm to my Native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try I was firſt to ſound; So diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging herein what I lay bound to, in the Peaceableneſs of my Mind, I retire into the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Choir, there waiting the bleſſed Iſſue and Succeſs of what hath been here from the pure Unction declar'd.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:151593:65"/>
                  <p>THE ARK of FAITH: OR A Supplement to the <hi>Tree of Faith,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>FOR THE Further Confirmation of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Together With A Diſcovery of the NEW WORLD.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>J. Lead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Faith</hi> Noah <hi>being warned of God, prepared an ARK to the ſaving of his Houſe; by the which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the World, and became Heir of the Righteouſneſs which is by Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>J. Bradford,</hi> in <hi>Jewen-Street,</hi> near <hi>Crowder's</hi>-Well, 1696.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:151593:66"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:151593:66"/>
                  <head>THE EDITOR TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>IT is hoped that this little Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, as well as the foregoing one, of which this is a Continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will not give Offence to any; but will afford matter of Joy and Comfort to very many, both in This, and in Several other Nations, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o whom they ſhall come. Since it ought not to be ſuppoſed, but that as many as profeſs themſelves to be Baptized into the Faith of JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,
<pb facs="tcp:151593:67"/>muſt be well enough ſatisfied to know what that Faith is, from ſuch as have been a long time expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced in it, who muſt be allowed certainly to be the moſt capable Judges in that, which is not to be Learned without a continual and unwearied Application: or to be Attained to, in the Practice, by any low Degrees of Aſſiduity, or by the ordinary Apprenticeſhip of a Few Years. And although by this Prepared Inſtrument of God, ſome great Depths of his Love have been already Publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Declared, which, not being apprehended, ſeem but <hi>Fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to the Wiſe of the World, and are a <hi>Stumbling block</hi> even to thoſe who call themſelves the Children of <hi>Abraham;</hi> theſe two Treatiſes being more Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimental cannot but find a more favourable Reception, if not
<pb facs="tcp:151593:67"/>from the former, yet at leaſt from the latter. However let it be as it will at the firſt, it is not at all to be feared but that God will vindicate what is from Him: and all the Promiſes in the Holy Scriptures being given to Faith, it cannot but reaſonably be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that he will do Right to one that is ſuch an Eminent Aſſerter of it, in an Age and Day, of which it hath been Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propheſied, that Faith ſhall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be found upon the Earth.</p>
                  <p>Whether it be not now high time for God to put to his Hand, and to manifeſt his Sovereign Authority by all ſuch Ways and Means, as he hath done of Old through the Operation of his own Faith, in all the great and mighty Elders of it: and <hi>to ſhew</hi> himſelf <hi>in the behalf of Truth and Goodneſs</hi> (as an
<pb facs="tcp:151593:68"/>Excellent Perſon, who was never Cenſured as I know of for an Enthuſiaſt expreſſeth it) <hi>which are ſo every where trampled on and deſpiſed, and to vindicate his own Honour from all thoſe Affronts and Contumelies, which ſtupid and Diſingenuous Men, which rebellious Spirits have caſt upon it;</hi> having made Shipwreck of the Faith that was delivered to them; deſerves well to be conſidered and weighted by every one. The Conſideration of which, as well as of the genuine Senſe of our Bleſſed Maſter's Words, made this moſt Judicious Author, to conclude all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans under a neceſſary and daily Obligation to ask of God, that he would be pleaſed to <hi>aſſert the Supream Authority of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment amongſt Men; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be by a FARTHER and
<pb facs="tcp:151593:68"/>CLEARER Manifeſtation of his Will, ſuch as was made by our Lord and his Holy Spirit; or whether ſome ACTS of Power be exerted for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and Preſervation of his Obedient Subjects,</hi> &amp;c. Dr. <hi>Burton,</hi> Of ſeeking firſt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, Publiſhed by <hi>J. TIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOTSON, 1684.</hi> p. <hi>402.</hi> Whence it is apparent that every true Chriſtian may, and ought to Pray, both for New Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, which may be of the ſame Authority as that by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and for Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Acts and Deeds, which may be a Declaration of God's Sovereignty and Kingdom. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo let thy Kingdom come, O God of the whole Earth: let it come even ſo: yea, Amen! Thou art King, let the Earth rejoice: yea, let the Great Iſles be glad
<pb facs="tcp:151593:69"/>thereof. <hi>Thine is the Kingdom,</hi> and thou wilt now take it to thy ſelf, let the People be never ſo Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient, yea, let them be never ſo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelieving. <hi>JEHOVAH</hi> Reigneth, let the People tremble, He ſitteth between the Cherubims, let the Earth ſtagger. Great wilt thou be O Lord in <hi>Sion,</hi> and thy Scepter ſhall be lifted up high above all the Nations. The Captives and Priſoners of Faith wilt thou ſet free, and thy Salvation unto them wilt thou openly ſhew, in the ſight of the very Infidels. Let the Sea of thy Love roar for Joy, and the Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof make a joyful Noiſe; for that the deſpiſed Ones who have Believed thee, wilt thou bring with triumph into the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Ark which thou haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them. With Trumpets and with the Voice of a Pſalm
<pb facs="tcp:151593:69"/>wilt thou bring them in: they ſhall clap their Hands aloud, they ſhall praiſe thy great and awful Name; for that thou, O Lord, art Faithful and True, and canſt not diſappoint any that have Faith in this thy Name. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Fire ſhall go before thee, and thy Meſſengers ſhalt thou ſend forth as Flames of Fire: Thou ſhalt ſpeak unto them as in the Cloudy Pillar, and they ſhall be kept as in the Ark of thy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. <hi>Samuel</hi> ſhall be ſeen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thy Prophets, and <hi>Elijah</hi> among thoſe that call upon the Lord of <hi>Iſrael; Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> among thy Prieſts, and great ſhall be the Company of the Preachers, to publiſh that our God liveth, and that our Life which was hidden in him ſhall be made to Appear with him. Out of <hi>Philadelphia</hi> ſhall thy Word go
<pb facs="tcp:151593:70"/>forth, and in <hi>Ramath</hi> of the Prophets ſhall thy Voice be known. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon Mount <hi>Sion</hi> ſhall they ſtand victoriouſly, they ſhall follow thee there in thy mighty Deeds, and from the Balmy Mountain of <hi>Gilead</hi> ſhall the precious Ointment diſtill. For in the Name of their God ſhall they caſt out Devils, they ſhall ſpeak with New Tongues: no Weapon formed againſt them ſhall be able to proſper, they ſhall take up Serpents, they ſhall drink any deadly thing; but nothing ſhall hurt them: they ſhall lay Hands on the Sick, and they ſhall recover. So ſhall they go forth, and Preach every where, the Lord working with them, and confirming the Word with the Signs that follow Faith.</p>
                  <p>Thus hath my Spirit been car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out, and conſtrained to
<pb facs="tcp:151593:70"/>bear this Teſtimony to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject here treated on, which is the Reſurrection of the Faith of <hi>JESUS,</hi> that has lain for a long time as it were in the Grave, and is now to be raiſed up early in the Third Day of the Holy Ghoſt. For which let us Watch, Wait and Pray, that we may be of the Firſt Fruits, of thoſe that are Riſen with him; that ſo we may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into Faith's Flying Ark here Deſcribed, which will tranſport us into the <hi>New Earth</hi> of Wonders, delivering us from the Deluge of the Curſe, that is from Infidelity.</p>
                  <p>When the Great Diary of this Author, or as much as can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered of it, ſhall come to be Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, the Several Progreſſes of this Life of Faith, the Various Manuductions for it, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe may conduce to its
<pb facs="tcp:151593:71"/>growth, will then more evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear: and all that which oppoſes the Secret and Hidden Divine Life, will be more eaſily Removed, and made to Vaniſh, then till then it can be. However to thoſe that have been iniſiated into the Myſtery of it, enough is ſaid: and it is not in the leaſt doubted, but that they will ſee what is Delivered both in the Former, and in This Treatiſe, to move upon a Real, Solid and Subſtantial Bottom; ſuch as all the Powers of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall be never able to ſhake, or the Gates and ſtrength of Hell to prevail againſt.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151593:71"/>
                  <head>THE Ark of Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">§. 1. THere is a Cry that hath gone forth from the Heavens theſe ſeveral Years paſt, for the Preparing and Building of an Ark for the Lord's redeemed Ones; and I am at this time, as the Natural Term of my Years ſeems to be expir'd, in order here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, again reminded of ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Prophecies, that were alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by me forgotten. But the Spirit of Wiſdom hath now preſented them afreſh to me, as telling me they were in this Day to be looked into, for Faith to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151593:72"/>be thence revived, and Prayer envigorated, that ſo the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Powers and Conſtellations co-operating therewithal, they might bring down the Golden Floods of Love to cover the Earth; that may bring up what hath lain under the Death, that is to ſay, a Reſurrection Body of pure Spirits in a new ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Paradiſe, which is the New Earth ſo much Propheſied of, upon which Righteouſneſs muſt dwell.</p>
                  <p n="2">§. 2. For the Signs of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Heavens do ſignifie out as much, that the Time is very near at hand for the Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of all theſe: for which End there was ſhewn to me an Ark in the Figure, but which was declared to me in the Myſtery to be no leſs then the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151593:72"/>Subſtance of the whole Triune Deity, who would ſuddenly ſend forth Ambaſſadours from themſelves, that are to be as the Firſt Fruits and Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives of the Bride to gather in all ſuch, as were to make up the whole <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> — Bride; whoſe Habitation is prepared in Wiſdom's Wonderful Paradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Principle.</p>
                  <p n="3">§. 3. Wherefore it was not long after I had received the firſt Manifeſtation and Figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Opening of Faith's <hi>TREE,</hi> from the Spirit of Faith grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up in me; before I had fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Notice given me, of an <hi>ARK,</hi> into which Faith's Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers who had hitten the Mark, were to be received in. For in a little more then a Year after that, I had this free Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151593:73"/>with my Lord concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, which follows: And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the latter Part of this, amongſt many other of my Papers, has been loſt, yet this which hath been by the All-wiſe Giver of it preſerved for that end, will, I know, be of ſome Service and Uſe; and therefore have I been prevailed with, to inſert it here, though I am not able to recal what either went before, or followed after it.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>February</hi> 21. 1687.</head>
                     <p n="4">§. 4. Being upon my Internal Watch in the pure ſtillneſs of my Mind, this Word came to me, ſaying, <hi>The Ark of Faith</hi> which the Lord hath been theſe many Years in raiſing and build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is yet not perſued, and as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151593:73"/>little underſtood, although War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upon Warning, and Sound upon Sound have gone forth for preparing and building ſuch an Ark, which may flote upon the broad River of the Holy Ghoſt: Then was I touched at this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my Lord, as being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious how he had opened to me this effectual Door, and Myſtery of Faith, charging me to keep to the Rules of it, which upon this Word I queſtioned whether I had kept up to ſo preciſely, as I had received command to do. Whereupon the Spirit pray'd in me, Lord God Omnipotent, if I have been negligent, ſhew it me: with much more to that effect, in which my Heart was enlarged to pray about it. Then was it in this wiſe revealed, and anſwered me: Thou haſt been learned and taught as another
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151593:74"/>
                        <hi>Noah</hi> to prepare and build an Ark of Faith in this Inviſible World: therefore ſlack not, but go on forward, and I will ſtrengthen the Studs and Stakes thereof, which ſhall be as ſtable as Gold, that ſhall be laid in as a firm bottom. Who further ſaid to me, That there was One known by Name, that ſhould have of the ſame Spirit of Faith to concur, and build with me, and ſo we ſhould be mutually made able to ſtrengthen one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others Hands, to carry on this great Work, as Male and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male in one Perſon, or Spirit, to enter firſt this Golden Ark of the Preſence, when reared up, for which we ſhould receive further Advertiſement, as we ſhould wait diligently here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:151593:74"/>§. 5. Then it aroſe further in me by way of Query, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound ſome things relating to this Fabrick unto the Great Maſter and Builder hereof; who anſwered me moſt freely, to whatever my Spirit was made to Inquire. But the Particulars of this matter being obliterated and paſſed away, the ſame Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Spirit that was then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with me, and ready to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate what was requiſite by me to be known, hath now (after many Years) revealed, and brought again to my Internal Sight, this Ark of Faith, in the enſuing manner; which I am commanded to declare and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, for the Information and Encouragement of all thoſe that ſeek to be redeemed from the Earth, and would enter into this Ark.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151593:75"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>February</hi> 18. 1695/6.</head>
                     <p n="6">§. 6. The Virgin Wiſdom founded a joyful Cry, ſaying, Come and ſee what an Ark is prepared for them that are Born into the Faith, as mighty Hero's to act the Wonders of the New Creation; which Ark is made in my New Paradiſe, that hath not yet been inhabited; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon great Floods came down from the Heavens as a Golden Rain; which covered the Face of the Mountains, as the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters did in <hi>Noah</hi>'s time drown the Old World: So that there was a mighty Sea, which was called the Love-Sea. Yet did it not as yet univerſally cover the Earth. Then after this did deſcend alſo this mighty Ark,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151593:75"/>in which was Faith's great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Noah,</hi> and all the High Elders of the Faith; which floated upon this Sea. This Ark was all of a moſt diapha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous fine Gold, with Six Wings on each ſide branching forth from it; ſo that it did Fly as well as Swim: which Wings were full of Eyes. Then was it ſaid to me, What doſt thou think this Ark is ſent down for, but to take in, and receive ſuch as have looked for Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be Saved from the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Curſe of the Old Earth, and from the Malignan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Venom of the Starry Kingdom? A loud Cry and Call then came out of the Ark, ſaying, Come, Haſten, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape for your Lives, for here is a Shelter prepared for you,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151593:76"/>while thoſe that do ſlight this Call, and have not Faith to fly away, muſt in another Deluge be ſwallowed up, which will be as the Waters in <hi>Noah</hi>'s Day, falling down upon them from the Starry Firmament, while the Children of Wiſdom's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who have obeyed her Voice, ſhall here be kept, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Wings of Power, which I had before ſeen, given to them, that they might fly into this Ark. Whereinto ſome Eminent in the Faith were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with great Acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Embracements, and theſe that firſt entred had great longings to attract in others af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them; which they waited here in hope to ſee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:151593:76"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>February</hi> the 19th.</head>
                     <p n="7">§. 7. Then the Great Captain of the Ark of Faith, Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, did ſteer the Ark, which with flying Wings did ſwiftly paſs, and landed us in the New Paradiſe. Where we were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Divine Magus's, and Maſters of the Faith, who underſtood the Myſtery of all Miraculous Faith. This was a wonderful Place, the like of which I had never ſeen, for the Walks were all paved as with Tranſparent Gold, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Temples were here, in which theſe Elders in Prieſtly Robes all glittering did pay their Homage to the Great and Mighty King, by whom they did work all their great Works,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151593:77"/>and give Exiſtency to that which never had been. Then were we led out to view the pleaſant Trees and Groves for delight and recreation: and the Trees did ſeem to be as of pure Gold, and the Branches to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den as with Diamonds, and all the variety of Precious Stones. Beſides which there were Trees alſo laden with all ſorts of preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fruits for Food: and Rivers with Fountains flowing with ſpic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Wine, and Cups and Flagons round about the Fountain. So we were called to drink at theſe Fountains, and to eat of theſe Fruits, being entertained by theſe Magi: to whoſe Care by the great Shepherd of this Fold we were committed. Who were to uſher us back to the Ark, to bring in others, and tranſport them hither. Which according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was done.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:151593:77"/>§. 8. After which it was ſaid to me, this Ark doth repreſent the Body of Faith, of which the Lord Chriſt is the Head, of whom the Church that is to be gathered into this is the Bride, the Lamb's Wife. Then did it float and fly with great force, with outſpread Banners: and a mighty Angel that was in it, did ſound forth his Trumpet, that all that would come out of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Confuſion, ſhould admittance have. At this Alarm came divers in, the mighty Spirit of <hi>Cyrus</hi> reſting upon ſome, the Spirit of <hi>Elijah</hi> upon others, of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and <hi>Zorobabel</hi> upon a third ſort, of <hi>Gideon, Barak</hi> and <hi>Deborah</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others of <hi>Miriam, Huldah, Dorcas</hi> and <hi>Lydia</hi> upon ſome; of <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Omeſimus</hi> upon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151593:78"/>others, with the beloved <hi>Mary, Martha</hi> and <hi>Hephzibah,</hi> with numerous others, both Males and Females that were unknown, of this and other Nations. For they flocked from the utmoſt Parts of the Earth as Doves to the Windows of this Ark, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard the report of this Good Land, from thoſe who had been ſent thither as Spies to ſeek it out. And when thus the Ark was filled, it was by a Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Angel ſitting at this Helm, Steered to this Paradiſical Land, where they were Landed with a joyful greeting; and had all their Tents here prepared for them; this being ſaid to be the Plantation for the Virgin <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphian</hi> Church, which has in former Treatiſe been Deſoribed.</p>
                     <p n="9">§. 9. And upon an Inquiry
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151593:78"/>made, whether all were now Landed? It was by the Spirit of Wiſdom, anſwered, No: For that the Ark was not to reſt, but to Fly and Float for more to be gathered in, till the Full Body of the Firſt Reſurrection ſtate was compleated, and brought hither, to put on their Immortal Robes, for the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Conſummation of the Marriage of the New <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> Bride. This is a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Myſtery, which in its Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling Day, will better be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood: for which we are to wait in great clarity of Mind, and ſanctity of Heart, in pure and perfect Dedication, and Seperation from all that is groſs and vulgar; for that none elſe can have admittance into this Holy Ark, but ſuch as are fully and wholly Purified by Faith.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:151593:79"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>February</hi> the 20th.</head>
                     <p n="10">§. 10. Here I thought to have ſtopped, as not knowing there ſhould be any further Addition from the Spirit of my Lord; but the next Morning, <hi>February</hi> 20. all was opened to me again, the Ark deſcending, and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion given from the Lord to the Beloved <hi>John,</hi> to ſteer it, with ſome Few Names born in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Love, and Practicioners of the High Myſtery of Faith, who were here with him to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide, and as Heraulds to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim the Love-Meſſage, and to call in ſuch as were willing upon the Report made concerning this New found Paradiſical Land, to leave the Land of the Curſe, and to wind themſelves
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151593:79"/>out of the Senſitive Principle, ſo as to be Diſciplined into the Faith. So accordingly as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port was made by theſe Perſons of what they had ſeen in this New Paradiſical Country, the ſtrength and power of Faith and Love did ſo manifeſtly appear, and give ſuch a Witneſs in thoſe that were in this Ark, that they did attract many from all Parts. And when the appointed num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was fulfilled, the beloved Great Apoſtle ſpread out the Wings of the Ark, in which were fixed the piercing Eyes, that did ſee the way by which they were to move till they came to this goodly Land; who then delivered up his Charge to the Princeſs and Governeſs of this Land. Who received all out here with an amiable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, telling them this Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151593:80"/>was of a Tranſmuting Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, which would put another kind of Body upon them, that ſhould be of ſuch Agility, Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Clarity, as the Old Body ſhould in all its Infirmities be ſwallowed up into this. Then was there given a Roll, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there was written certain Rules, which they were to Act, and be Practioners in, as the Laws of this Kingdom, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Kingly Shepherd himſelf did give them a Pattern, and ſaid, Ye are to Act and Work, as my ſelf have done and acted, as an obedient Son to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. What ye have ſeen me do, that are ye alſo to do, as Followers of me: for hitherto the Father worketh, and I work, and ye muſt be fellow-workers with me, as riſen with me: and ſo muſt all your Works now be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151593:80"/>by the Faith of my Operation in you. Then the Roll was Read to theſe that were now Landed, as it had been to thoſe that were before admitted to be Inhabitants.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:151593:81"/>
                     <head>The Laws of the High and Holy Calling, that are to be Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by thoſe that are admitted into this Paradifical Land.</head>
                     <p n="11">§. 11. <hi>THeſe are the Particulars of that Holy Calling, which all are in this Place to Profeſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <hi>I. The Firſt of theſe, is to learn of me, (ſaith</hi> JESUS) <hi>to be Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Meek in Spirit, even as I am, being contented with no leſſer Degree. For this is the firſt Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Qualification: for as much as my Lily grows only out of ſuch a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151593:81"/>Ground as is all leavened, and of an even Temperature, neither too Hot or Cold, Moiſt or Dry; but found always in Contrition and Humility: from whence Exaltation to Higher things will certainly ariſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <hi>II. The Second Degree which ye are to take from hence, is to know how to underſtand the Manual Operation of the Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d of Faith, by which the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tent muſt be wrought for <hi>Shem</hi> and</hi> Japheth <hi>to dwell together in great and full enlargement. For through the Exerciſe and nimble Activity of this Hand, all Proviſions neceſſary will be brought in for the Bridegroom and Bride to live upon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <hi>III. A Third Particular relating to your High Calling is to attend, and officiate in the moſt Holy Inward Court,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151593:82"/>there to wait, and be at hand to receive evermore freſh Command: as alſo to hear, and learn what further is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to reach to the higheſt Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment towards Natures moſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Reſtauration.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <hi>IV. The Fourth Particular, or Law, is to come to a putting forth of all the Eſſential Properties into Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, according to what ye have ſeen, and been inſtructed in from the Father and me; ſtirring up the Gift, that ſo it may not lie uſeleſs in you in any Degree.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <hi>V. Ye are not to think it ſufficient that ye have Learned Part of my Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; but ye are i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>is Place to learn All, even to the full <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Example which I have ſet you. Therefore come, ſet your Hand
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151593:82"/>of Faith to Work and Act, as I your Lord have done; who expect you ſhould come up to thoſe Meaſures I have ſet before you: who am, and will be to you, the ſame flowing Sourſe of Life-quickning Power, if called out, that I was when planted in your Likeneſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Behold! I am at hand to do as great and mighty Works, as ye are able to receive. So will I imprint not only the Image of Purity, but of Power upon you; that ſo ye may full out be made Partakers of my Profeſſion. Which doth not only conſiſt in Love, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Gentleneſs, Patience, Wiſdom, and Soundneſs of Judgment, but alſo in the Faith of the Omnipotency. For in my Calling it is only requiſite to have Light and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, to find out the Myſtery of this High Art, but Strength and Might to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151593:83"/>Work out the ſame from the Eternal <hi>Magia</hi> Root; from whence the Birth of Power doth proceed. Now before ye can Proficients and Practitioners in all things anſwerable to your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident herein be; ye muſt come to be ſtrong, and find ability to turn about that which moveth the Creating Word: by which all loſt Dominion may be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed. But what can draw forth that, except it be ſomewhat, that is Equal in Might with it ſelf; which will be found out if the Will-Spirit ſinks deep into its own Central Root. From whence the Life ſappy-Power may ſpring, which will do Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles at Will. This was the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Work and Buſineſs belonging to my Calling, which on the Earth I did, and yet do, appear again to walk, and to be admired through the raiſing again of this Mighty Power, which in all
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151593:83"/>of you ſhall wonderfully work, that have ceaſed now to live promiſcuouſly in that low Temporizing State, which I have called you out of: that ſo capable ye might be of this Worthy and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Vocation; exactly in, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to, the Method that I have ſhewn to you: That ſo not only in the Hopes circling about, but coming to the very Manual Exerciſes themſelves, ye may reap, and live upon the Benefits which this Pure Abſtracted Calling ſhall and will abundantly bring in, and not only bare Grain, that is for and to your own Accounts; which the leaſt in your Eye muſt be.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <hi>VI. For</hi> Abel-<hi>like ye are to bring the Firſt Fruits of this high extracted Calling, to ſacrifice all in a flaming Oily Perfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> unto your Great</hi> Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedeck.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:151593:84"/>
                        <hi>VII. Further ye are Excited to feed upon no other Fruits, but what the Tree of Faith doth give forth. I am that Tree which ye muſt feed upon all other Trees forbidden are, which cheriſh up the Life of Senſibility. Therefore fix your Eye, and center your Heart upon that which may nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh up this Birth of Faith, till it reach to its full Maturity: then will it come to underſtand what Sovereignty and Dominion it is entituled to, as a King and Lord over all.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="12">§. 12. Then Queried I with my Lord, <hi>What was meant by thoſe Trees which I had ſeen all laden with Precious Stones, and the Trunks of them of ſuch fine Gold?</hi> To which it was An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered me, that thoſe did run
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151593:84"/>Parallel with the <hi>New Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> repreſenting the Bride of the Lamb that was thus to be adorned. For it was ſhewn me, that theſe Trees were Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative Figures of thoſe that were brought into the Ark, and here Landed; whoſe Cloathing was to be in ſuch variety of Sparkling Glory, that from the Golden Sap of Faith ſhould be always freſh and flouriſhing.</p>
                     <p n="13">§. 13. Then I Queried further of him that ſhewed me theſe things, <hi>Whether it were poſſible for Mortals, whoſe dwelling was in this lower World, to know ſuch a Tranſlation as this?</hi> It was hereupon Replyed, There is no leſs a thing deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: the Time and Age for this is already come to ſome, that in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151593:85"/>the Inward Figure as Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives ſtand, who are in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit tranſported into this Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Land. But in obſcurity they muſt be, till the Hand of Power ſhall rend away the Veil, that hath upon this Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a Covering been; but yet the Faith is growing, and when to a full Body of Strength it ſhall reach, then ſhall ye ſee the Wonders fly from each of theſe bright luſtrous Trees, which in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> New Paradiſical Earth ſhall multiply numerouſly.</p>
                     <p n="14">§. 14. It was then further ſaid, To you that attentive are to theſe my Sayings, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſhall be to my Rules, I will put no other Burthen upon you, but to hold faſt the Faith, that ſpringeth from the Golden
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151593:85"/>Stem of Love; wherein your Strength ſhall be as Anointed Cherubs ſtill to move, your Reſt to find in me, where no Annoyance can ever be. For this is a New Time, in which the New World will appear: therefore ſpare ye not it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, and proclaim. By this now let all underſtand, what a wonderful Time is at the Door.</p>
                     <p n="15">§. 15. Upon which my Spirit was carried to cry, O Mighty <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> Ariſe thou and Gather in, by thy great Power and Strength, into this Ark ſuch as are to make up the Firſt Reſurrection-Body; to whom thou wilt be the Head, the Crown, the Joy and the Glory. Verily, this is the Time in which thou wilt ſend forth thy Meſſengers that ſhall ſound the Jubilee Horn, and pour out therefrom that rich Anointing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151593:86"/>Oil to conſecrate a Prieſtly Race, that ſhall no other thing mind, but to purſue, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after that which is highly Divine. For which there is this Day great Travail: O God, let not the Lordly Birth, which is the King and Heir of Faith, any longer ſtick: let thy Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Arm and Hand take hold of it, that no more drawings back there may be, but the Son of Joy and Laughter we may ſee. For ſurely the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Bride preparing is her ſelf, in expectation that her Kingly Bridegroom will no longer ſtay, but make ſpeed and come away; that all Redeemed from the Earth may be, that have waited in the Faith this Reſurrection-State to ſee. And in this New World, do thou, O great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, plant us, as Trees of Righteouſneſs and Glory, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cling
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151593:86"/>about thee, who the over-ſpreaking Tree of Life, and ſplendorous Bightneſs art, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe Shadow we ſhall grow moſt fruitfully.</p>
                     <p n="16">§. 16. Neither pray we alone for theſe Firſt Fruits, but that a plentious new Sowing of thy Spirit may go forth, to bring in the reſt of the Harveſt, that lieth yet as under Death and Barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For thou haſt ſaid thy Ark ſhall not take up its Reſt till it hath made its flight to all Corners of the Earth. The Trumpet of thy Love ſhall ſuch a loud Cry ſend forth, throughout all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that conſtrained they may be, to fly as ſwift Dromedaries, and bring their Offerings into thy ſacred Ark. Even ſo, Bleſſed JESUS, let all theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies fulfilled be, both what hath been in paſt Ages given, and hath been of late ſo plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151593:87"/>Renewed, through them whom thou haſt for this end choſen, though not worthy to be named, yet known by Name in thy Book of Life, which ſufficient is: who ſhall never ceaſe, or any Reſt take up in, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til thou haſt made a Glorious Spotleſs Church upon the Earth to appear, as a Flying Ark with Banners, whoſe Eyes as Lamps of Fire may go forth, to gather in the whole Prieſtly and Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hoſt, from all Quarters and Parts of the Earth. Even ſo, with thy Triumphant Church,</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Shall we the Song of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption Sing</l>
                        <l>Glory, Glory, Glory to the Triune King.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>Even ſo: <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="by_the_same_author">
                  <pb facs="tcp:151593:87"/>
                  <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
                  <p>WHereas ſome Things have been Scandalouſly ſet forth, and Printed under the Name of this Author to the Reproach of Truth, and the Diſhonour of that which is Holy, it is thought fit for the putting a Stop to ſuch Impoſtures, and the Evil which might thence enſue, to give a Catalogue of the <hi>Books</hi> which the Author hath hitherto Publiſhed.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>THE Heavenly Cloud,</hi> or, <hi>the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion Ladder,</hi> 4to. 1682. p. 40.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Revelation of Revelations,</hi> an Eſſay towards the Unſealing, Open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Diſcovering of the Seven Seals, the Seven Thunders, and the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> State. 4to. 1683. p. 130.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Enochian Walks with God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ound out by a Spiritual Traveller. 4to. 1694. p. 38.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Laws of Paradiſe;</hi> Given forth by Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to a Tranſlated Spirit. 8vo. 1695. p. 69.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Wonder of God's Creation manifeſted in the Variety of Eight Worlds,</hi> as they were made known Experimentally to the Author. 8vo. 1695. p. 89.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:151593:88"/>
                        <hi>The Meſſage to the</hi> Philadelphian <hi>Society,</hi> whitherſoever diſperſed over the whole Earth, together with a Call to the ſeveral gathered Churches. 12ves. p. 108. 1696.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Tree of Faith:</hi> or the Tree of Life, ſpringing up in the Paradiſe of God; from which all the Wonders of the New Creation muſt proceed 12ves. p. 122. 1696.</item>
                     <item>The Ark of Faith. p. 33.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:151593:88"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
